<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mene tekel, or, The council of officers of the Army, against the declarations, &amp;c. of the Army. Wherein is flatly proved by the express words of the Armies declarations, that the sixth article of the * late address of the said council of officers to the Parliament, point-blank changeth the cause of liberty of conscience, from the good old one, to a bad new one; from that which at first, and all along the Army engaged in, and for, and declared to that which they engaged against. Moreover, that the imposition therein is agreeable neither to the Armies solemn declarations and engagements, nor to liberty of conscience, nor to the Scriptures of truth, but is contrary to them all ... Geo. Bishop.</title>
            <author>Bishop, George, d. 1668.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76758</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3000</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E999_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207833</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866861</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866861</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119149</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76758)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119149)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 148:E999[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mene tekel, or, The council of officers of the Army, against the declarations, &amp;c. of the Army. Wherein is flatly proved by the express words of the Armies declarations, that the sixth article of the * late address of the said council of officers to the Parliament, point-blank changeth the cause of liberty of conscience, from the good old one, to a bad new one; from that which at first, and all along the Army engaged in, and for, and declared to that which they engaged against. Moreover, that the imposition therein is agreeable neither to the Armies solemn declarations and engagements, nor to liberty of conscience, nor to the Scriptures of truth, but is contrary to them all ... Geo. Bishop.</title>
                  <author>Bishop, George, d. 1668.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed, and are to be sold by Tho. Brewster, at the Three Bibles, by Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The asterisk in title refers to printed marginal note: *May 12. 1659.</note>
                  <note>The words "The council .. Army," and "the declarations, .. Army." are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept 29.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119149:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MENE TEKEL, OR, The <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Officers</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> Againſt The <hi>Declarations,</hi> &amp;c. of the <hi>Army.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WHEREIN Is <hi>flatly</hi> proved by the <hi>expreſs</hi> Words of the <hi>Armies</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, that the <hi>Sixth</hi> Article of the <note n="*" place="margin">May 12. 1659.</note> 
               <hi>late Addreſs</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Officers</hi> to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> point-blank changeth the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> from the <hi>Good Old One,</hi> to a <hi>Bad New One;</hi> from <hi>that</hi> which at <hi>firſt,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> along the <hi>Army</hi> engaged in, and for, and Declared to <hi>that</hi> which <hi>they</hi> engaged againſt.</p>
            <p>MOREOVER, That the <hi>Impoſition</hi> therein is agreeable neither to the <hi>Armies</hi> ſolemn Declarations and Engagements, nor to <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> nor to the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> but is contrary to them <hi>All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>DIRECTED To the ſaid <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Officers,</hi> for their Convincement.</p>
            <p>AND PUBLISHED For the <hi>Information</hi> of <hi>all</hi> who are concern'd in the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>GEO. BISHOP.</p>
            <q>—Heù quantum Mutat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sab illo?</q>
            <q>For if I build again the things I deſtroyed, I make my ſelf a Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſor, <bibl>Gal. 2. 18.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by <hi>Tho. Brewſter,</hi> at the <hi>Three Bibles,</hi> by <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:119149:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:119149:2"/>
            <head>TO THE COUNCIL OF THE Officers of the Army.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>FRIENDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving ſeen <hi>Your</hi> late <hi>humble Petition</hi> and <hi>Addreſs</hi> to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and conſidered the Matter and Language of the <hi>Sixth</hi> Article, <hi>I</hi> was grieved in <hi>my</hi> ſpirit (for your ſakes) to ſee that <hi>ye</hi> ſhould be ſo quickly removed from <hi>your</hi> Stedfaſtneſs to the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> contained in <hi>your</hi> Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and engaged in a <hi>New,</hi> (as <hi>this</hi> more than ſeems to be, and <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſhew it you by and by) even that of <hi>your</hi> enemies, in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the former, and ſo provoke the <hi>Lord</hi> to anger againſt <hi>your</hi> Selves, whoſe loving kindneſs hath ſo <hi>tenderly</hi> viſited <hi>you,</hi> when <hi>ye</hi> cryed unto him becauſe of <hi>your</hi> Oppreſſion, who heard and delivered <hi>you.</hi> Therefore bear with <hi>me,</hi> whilſt in <hi>bowels of love, I</hi> lay before <hi>you</hi> the <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>other,</hi> to the end, that <hi>ye</hi> may ſee <hi>your</hi> State, and be recovered out of the Snare, in which <hi>ye</hi> are taken captive by the ſubtilty of men, who lay in wait to deceive, and ſo repenting, the judgment of <hi>God,</hi> which is ready to break forth, may be turned from <hi>you.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:119149:3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Ye</hi> know (<hi>Friends</hi>) that the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> was (chiefly) <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> which being oppreſſed by the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>that</hi> Generation, cryed out ſo loud, as raiſed the <hi>firſt</hi> War, on the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Kings</hi> part, to oppreſs and keep <hi>it</hi> under; on the <hi>Parliaments,</hi> to defend and deliver it, and the <hi>Liberties</hi> of the <hi>Nation, which</hi> with the <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> were bound up, and joyned together, as two <hi>lovely Twins</hi> that cannot be divided, but with the <hi>mutual</hi> Suffering, if not the <hi>Diſſolution</hi> of each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Biſhops Yoaks</hi> of <hi>Wood</hi> being taken off <hi>ſome,</hi> who (but now) Suffered under <hi>them,</hi> riſe up in <hi>their</hi> ſteads to oppreſs <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;</hi> and <hi>theſe</hi> prepare other <hi>yoaks, yoaks</hi> of <hi>Iron,</hi> for the necks of <hi>their</hi> Brethren, who Suffered in, and with <hi>them,</hi> and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether fought for <hi>equal</hi> Liberty; and nothing would ſerve <hi>theſe</hi> (who Suffered <hi>themſelves</hi> but yeſterday, as it were for <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi>) but to bring the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of <hi>all</hi> others to <hi>their</hi> ſize, the Souls of <hi>all,</hi> to <hi>their</hi> Diametre or ſquare, who differed from <hi>them,</hi> or the <hi>Nations</hi> muſt ſwim in blood, and peace be denied <hi>them;</hi> as if the <hi>Cauſe</hi> engaged in, had been, that <hi>they</hi> might have <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and that it was ſo to be, and as of right, and the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of <hi>all</hi> others made <hi>their Slaves</hi> and <hi>Vaſſals,</hi> (a more <hi>arrogant</hi> and <hi>unſufferable</hi> Uſurpation, in <hi>theſe</hi> than the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> by how much the more <hi>they</hi> cryed out againſt, and oppoſed <hi>it</hi> in <hi>them.</hi>) Hence it came to paſs, that <hi>they</hi> ſo ſoon divided from the <hi>joynt</hi> proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>common Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Liberty,</hi> (to the hazzard of the <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi>), diſtinguiſhing <hi>themſelves</hi> and <hi>others</hi> into <hi>terms</hi> and <hi>things,</hi> and endeavouring the ſetting up <hi>their</hi> private upon <hi>it,</hi> with ſuch <hi>imperious</hi> Lordlineſs, as <hi>no</hi> Age hath pararell'd: and when as the <hi>moſt deſired peace,</hi> was trilling down the <hi>Mountains</hi> of <hi>Blood,</hi> to the <hi>weary</hi> Inhabitans of <hi>theſe</hi> Nations, who had <hi>tugg'd</hi> hard for <hi>it,</hi> through the <hi>extremities</hi> of <hi>War, it</hi> muſt all be turned back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and the <hi>Bloody</hi> iſſue again opened, and the <hi>common</hi> Enemy joyned with, (after <hi>he</hi> was overthrown) <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> raiſed up, and aſſiſted for that purpoſe, againſt <hi>thoſe</hi> of <hi>their</hi> Brethren, who continued <hi>faithful,</hi> and were <hi>bleſſed</hi> of God, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>they</hi> were ſo <hi>bleſt</hi> againſt <hi>their</hi> wills, and endeavours to the contrary) to the overthrowing of the <hi>common</hi> Enemy; and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver would <hi>they</hi> be at reſt (ſo ſtrange was <hi>their itch</hi> at the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences</hi> of <hi>others,</hi> and ſo inſatiable <hi>their</hi> deſires, to be dealing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119149:3"/> with the <hi>Souls</hi> of men, who, yet injoyed the <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>their</hi> own) raiſing and carrying on <hi>War</hi> after <hi>War,</hi> till <hi>they</hi> were all vanquiſht, and <hi>their</hi> whole ſtrength together broken down, at <hi>Worceſter,</hi> which quickly ended the <hi>Wars</hi> in theſe Nations.</p>
            <p>Thus (<hi>Friends</hi>) briefly, as to the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> or <hi>State</hi> of the <hi>Caſe</hi> in reference to <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and the <hi>publick Conteſt</hi> thereabouts, in <hi>which</hi> how deeply <hi>ye</hi> were concerned, <hi>viz.</hi> in the <hi>former</hi> as <hi>Puritans, Non-conformiſts,</hi> and <hi>factious Fellows,</hi> (ſo <hi>called</hi> and <hi>perſecuted</hi>) in <hi>common</hi> with the reſt: in the <hi>latter,</hi> as <hi>Hereticks,</hi> and <hi>Schiſmaticks, I</hi> ſhall not, (nor need <hi>I</hi>) further to repeat. Theſe things (<hi>I</hi> may well preſume) are engraven in <hi>you,</hi> in an <hi>indeleble</hi> Charecter; Nor ſhall <hi>I</hi> treat, how honeſt men in <hi>theſe</hi> Nations, joyned with and aſſiſted <hi>you,</hi> for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as in a <hi>common</hi> Cauſe, wherein <hi>they</hi> and <hi>you</hi> were ſo <hi>equally</hi> concerned, as that <hi>One</hi> could not fall or miſcarry, without the dammage, or the detriment of the <hi>Other;</hi> how readily <hi>they</hi> flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>you,</hi> whilſt that moved <hi>you</hi> to any <hi>extraordinary</hi> actions; and what <hi>grief</hi> of heart <hi>it</hi> occaſioned to <hi>them,</hi> and <hi>ſufferings,</hi> when <hi>ye</hi> have, at any time ſwerved therefrom, is manifeſt; the things are <hi>freſh,</hi> and but of <hi>yeſterday,</hi> the <hi>late</hi> Revolutions ſpeak them ſufficiently; but this <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſhew <hi>you</hi> plainly out of <hi>your</hi> own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, and in <hi>your</hi> own words, how <hi>this</hi> Article <hi>changeth</hi> the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> from the <hi>Old,</hi> to a <hi>New;</hi> from a <hi>good Old one,</hi> to a <hi>bad New one,</hi> from <hi>that</hi> in which at <hi>firſt,</hi> and all along <hi>ye</hi> engaged for, and in; to <hi>another,</hi> to <hi>that</hi> againſt which <hi>ye</hi> engaged. And <hi>this I</hi> ſhall endeavour to do, with as much brevity, as the <hi>weight</hi> of the <hi>Caſe</hi> will admit, not clogging <hi>ye</hi> with a <hi>large</hi> Recital, of <hi>all</hi> that <hi>ye</hi> have ſaid in <hi>this</hi> particular, (though what <hi>ye</hi> have taken liberty to ſpeak, <hi>ye</hi> ſhould endure to hear) But contracting the proof of what <hi>I</hi> have laid down, to <hi>two</hi> of <hi>your</hi> Declarations, as <hi>my two in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> or <hi>witneſſes,</hi> viz. <hi>The great Remonſtrance St. Albans,</hi> Nov. 16. 1648. and <hi>your draught of the Settlement of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Whitehal,</hi> Jan. 15. 1649. <hi>Both</hi> drawn up by <hi>you,</hi> and preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>this</hi> Parliament, upon <hi>two</hi> of the <hi>moſt</hi> weighty occaſions <hi>ye</hi> (then) had met withal, and the <hi>greateſt</hi> Subjects; The <hi>one</hi> the the <hi>bringing</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> to <hi>juſtice,</hi> and <hi>changing</hi> of the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> into <hi>that</hi> of a <hi>free State</hi> or <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> upon <hi>which ye</hi> pretend to build, now that <hi>ye</hi> are returned <hi>thither</hi> again; The <hi>other, your aſſerting</hi> after the (then) <hi>Wars,</hi> and the <hi>Juſtice</hi> done
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119149:4"/> on the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>change</hi> of the <hi>Government</hi> thereupon) what <hi>your</hi> ſelves and the <hi>People</hi> did expect, and ought to reap of <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty therefrom,</hi> and <hi>Right</hi> as to <hi>All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> in the <hi>Sum</hi> of the <hi>Publick</hi> Intreſt (<hi>which had been the great Subject of the conteſt all along, in the late Wars</hi>) drawn up by <hi>you</hi> in <hi>your</hi> ſaid <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> and laid down, as that which (<hi>ye</hi> ſay) the <hi>King</hi> had <hi>all along oppoſed, to ſet up his, and his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities Will and Power;</hi> and whereupon <hi>ye</hi> ground <hi>your</hi> charge againſt <hi>him, ye</hi> aſſign nothing (in the leaſt) of <hi>power</hi> in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> (that there <hi>was,</hi> or <hi>ought</hi> to <hi>be any</hi> ſuch, or that <hi>it</hi> was <hi>any</hi> part of the <hi>Conteſt</hi>) to <hi>impoſe</hi> in <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience;</hi> but charge <hi>him</hi> with the <hi>oppoſing the Reformation in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and endeavoured by the Parliament, (as their proper work)</hi> of <hi>what he</hi> had <hi>impoſed</hi> in <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the <hi>proof</hi> of <hi>this,</hi> ſee what <hi>ye</hi> have ſaid, <hi>Remonſtrance,</hi> pag. 14, 15. <hi>The ſum of the publick Intereſt,</hi> (ſay ye) <hi>of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in relation to Common Right and Freedome, (which hath been the chief ſubject of our Conteſt) and in oppoſition to Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Injuſtice, in Kings and Others, we take to lie in theſe things following; That for all matters of Supream Power, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, to the ſafety and welfare of the whole, the People have a Common or Supream Council; and that the power of making Laws, Conſtitutions, and Offices (for the Preſervation and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the whole) and of altering, repealing, and aboliſhing the ſame, (for the removing of any publick grievànce therein) and the power of final Judgment concerning War, or Peace, the ſafety or welfare of the People, and all [Civil] things whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vir,</hi> (here's not a <hi>tittle</hi> of Religious) <hi>without further appeal to any created ſtanding Power; and the Supream Truſt, in relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all ſuch things, may reſt in that Supream Council.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>this</hi> it is plain, that to <hi>Settle,</hi> or <hi>Create</hi> a <hi>Power</hi> in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> to <hi>impoſe</hi> in <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> or <hi>Conſcience,</hi> was <hi>no</hi> part of the <hi>publick</hi> Intereſt in <hi>conteſt</hi> in the <hi>Wars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, that the <hi>King</hi> had <hi>impoſed</hi> in <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>oppoſed the Reformation intended and endeavoured by the Parliament,</hi> of what <hi>he</hi> had ſo <hi>impoſed:</hi> Here what <hi>ye</hi> alſo ſay in <hi>your</hi> own words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Matters aforementioned</hi> (ſay ye <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Remonſtrance St.</hi> Albans, page 18.</note> to the Parliament) <hi>being the main parts of Publick Intereſt originally contended for on our
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119149:4"/> parts, and them that engaged with you,</hi> (viz. the Parliament) <hi>and thus oppoſed by the King, for the Intereſt of his Will and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer: many other particular, or ſpecial Intereſts have fallen into</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Page 20.</note> 
               <hi>the conteſt on each Party; As firſt, on the Parliaments part, to protect and countenance religious men, and godlineſs in the power of it,</hi> (Who hath diſcountenanced and put ſuch out of protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (Now?) to the witneſs of God in you all I ſpeak.) <q>
                  <hi>To give freedome and enlargement to the Goſpel, for the encreaſing and ſpreading of Light amonſt men,</hi>
               </q> (Who endeavours to ſtop it now?) <hi>To take away thoſe corrupted Forms of an out-ſide Religion, and Church-Government, whether impoſed without a Law, or rooted in the Law in times of Popiſh ignorance and Idolatry, or of the Goſpels dimmer light,</hi> (Who eſtabliſhes ſuch now? whoſe light is dim now?) <hi>By means whereof chains and ſnares, were laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſcientious and zealous men,</hi> (Who have laid chains and ſnares for ſuch men now?) <hi>And the generality of the People held in darkneſs and ſuperſtition, and a blind Reverence of perſons, and outward things, fit for Popery and Slavery,</hi> (Who holds them ſo now, and fits them for ſuch?) <hi>And alſo to take away, and looſen the dependance of the Clergy, and Eccleſiaſtical affairs on the King,</hi> (Who hath put it on the Magiſtrate, yea as the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of a Free State (declared ſo) now?) <hi>Which the craft of both in length of time had wrought for each other,</hi> (How crept it in? and by whoſe craft hath it wrought it ſo, and in ſo ſhort a ſpace now? <hi>Which ſeveral things were the proper ſubject of the Reformation endeavoured by the Parliament,</hi> (Who hath pray'd the Parliament to do, and at whoſe addreſs and requeſt have they done the contrary now?) <hi>Contrariwiſe on the Kings Party,</hi> (Whoſe Party is it now become, and Intereſt? Who is it now that hath laid a foundation for the following particulars?) <hi>The Intereſt was to diſcountenance and ſuppreſs the power of godlineſs, or any thing of Conſcience obliging above, or againſt humane and outward Conſtitutions; to reſtrain or leſſen the preaching of the Goſpel, and growth of light among men; To hold the Community of men in a darksome ignorance, and ſuperſtition, or formality in Religion, with an awful Reverence of Perſons, Offices, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward diſpenſations (rendring them ſit ſubjects for Eccleſiaſtical and Civil Tyranny) And for theſe ends to advance, and ſet up further forms of Superſtition, or at leaſt hold faſt the old, which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119149:5"/> had any foundation in the Laws (whereby chains and fetters might be held upon, and advantages taken againſt ſuch in whom a zeal or Conſcience to any thing above man, ſhould break forth) and to uphold and maintain the dependance of the Clergy and Church matters on the King, and greatneſs of the Clergy under him,</hi> (Who hath done, and is doing all this now?) <hi>And in all theſe things to oppoſe the Reformation endeavoured by the Parliament,</hi> (Who hath ſet the Parliament now to oppoſe the very Reformation themſelves endeavoured, of which (ye ſay) it was the <hi>proper ſubject.</hi>) Read <hi>theſe</hi> things in the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of <hi>honeſty,</hi> in which <hi>ye</hi> wrote it, and then read <hi>your</hi> ſelves, and ſee how <hi>you</hi> are (in a moment, as it were) beguiled and ſurprized (after all) and dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened into the <hi>Kings</hi> Intereſt, (as <hi>ye your</hi> ſelves have here <hi>ſtated</hi> it) out of and from the <hi>Parliaments,</hi> doing <hi>your</hi> ſelves the <hi>very</hi> things, with which <hi>ye</hi> here charge <hi>him,</hi> and for which (among other things) <hi>ye</hi> took <hi>him</hi> off: The <hi>matters</hi> are <hi>ſo</hi> plain and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, as they need no further demonſtration: Conſider <hi>them</hi> ſeriouſly in the <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> for <hi>it</hi> is no <hi>ſlight</hi> thing that <hi>ye</hi> are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into; But <hi>that</hi> on which doth hang the <hi>guilt</hi> of <hi>all</hi> the <hi>blood</hi> that hath been <hi>ſhed</hi> in the <hi>late</hi> Wars, <hi>ye</hi> have given <hi>Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> againſt <hi>your</hi> ſelves in the <hi>Caſe,</hi> in this <hi>your</hi> Judgment againſt the <hi>King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> ſhall cloſe <hi>this</hi> inſtance with <hi>your</hi> own words, in the cloſe of this particular, (pag. 21.) <hi>In all or moſt of which reſpects</hi> (ſay ye) of what hath been repeated) <hi>it hath been the great happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and advantage to Parliamentary and publick Intereſt, that it hath been made One, very much, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Intereſt of the godly, or, (for the name whereof, it hath been ſo much derided) the Saints; as on the other ſide, the Kings, one with their greateſt oppoſites; By occaſion whereof, God hath been doubly engaged in the Cauſe,</hi> viz. <hi>for that, and the righteouſneſs of it) and to this indeed, (through the favour and preſence of God therewith) the Parliament hath cauſe to own, and refer the bleſſing and ſucceſs, that hath accompanied their affairs, which (accordingly as they have held ſquare, and been kept cloſe to this) have proſpered glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, and wherein, or ſo oft as this hath been thwarted, ſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from or neglected in their mannage) have ſuffered miſerable blaſtings.</hi> Read <hi>your</hi> Sentence thus pronounced by <hi>your</hi> ſelves, and <hi>fear</hi> before the <hi>Lord,</hi> and bear <hi>your</hi> ſhame, and caſt out the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119149:5"/> 
               <hi>unclean black Spirit,</hi> that bewitched <hi>you</hi> into <hi>this,</hi> the <hi>Serpent</hi> that hath beguiled <hi>you,</hi> leaſt the <hi>anger</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie <hi>Smoak</hi> againſt <hi>you,</hi> and there be <hi>no</hi> remedy.</p>
            <p>Thus much of <hi>my Firſt</hi> inſtance, <hi>my Second</hi> follows.</p>
            <p>In <hi>your</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">See the Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, preſented the Parliament Saturday, <hi>Jan.</hi> 20. 1649. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the draught of an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement of the people for a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent peace, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſaid agreement.</note> 
               <hi>Settlement</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> (ſo called by <hi>your</hi> ſelves) <hi>for a ſecure</hi> and <hi>preſent Peace, upon grounds of Common Right, Freedome, and Safety, as a fruit of their Labours, Hazzards,</hi> and <hi>Sufferings, that have engaged in the common Cauſe; as ſome Price of the Blood ſpilt, and Ballance to the Publick expence,</hi> and <hi>Dammage ſuſtained in the War;</hi> and <hi>as ſome due Improvement, of that ſucceſs</hi> and <hi>bleſſing, God hath pleaſed to give them,</hi> (as are <hi>your</hi> words in the draught thereof; (Pag. 7) and in the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration</hi> thereunto annext, (Pag. 27.) which <hi>ye</hi> preſented <hi>this</hi> Parliament, <hi>Jan.</hi> 20. 1649. and deſired (in the <hi>Petition</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal <hi>ye</hi> preſented it, <hi>Pag.</hi> 5, 6.) that whether <hi>it</hi> ſhould be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ully approved by <hi>them,</hi> and received by the <hi>People,</hi> (as then <hi>it</hi> ſtood) yet <hi>it</hi> might <hi>remain</hi> upon <hi>Record</hi> before <hi>them,</hi> a <hi>Perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al witneſs</hi> of <hi>your real</hi> intentions, and <hi>utmoſt</hi> endeavours, for a <hi>ſound and equal Settlement,</hi> and as a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> whereby <hi>all</hi> men might be <hi>aſſured,</hi> what <hi>ye</hi> were <hi>willing</hi> and <hi>ready</hi> to <hi>acquieſs</hi> in; and <hi>their</hi> Jealouſies ſatisfied, or mouths ſtopt, who were apt to think and ſay, <hi>ye</hi> had no bottome. <hi>I</hi> ſay, in <hi>your</hi> ſaid <hi>Settlement ye</hi> are ſo far from <hi>Aſſigning</hi> any <hi>Power</hi> at all, to the <hi>Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives</hi> of the <hi>People,</hi> of <hi>Impoſing</hi> in <hi>Matters</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, things Spiritual</hi> or <hi>Evangelical;</hi> or granting <hi>it</hi> (in the leaſt) to be <hi>any</hi> part of the <hi>Publick</hi> intereſt, which had been the <hi>Subject</hi> of the <hi>conteſt,</hi> that <hi>ye poſitively</hi> exclude and bar <hi>them</hi> from <hi>it</hi> for ever. For <hi>this</hi> ſee what <hi>your</hi> ſelves have ſaid, and conclude <hi>your</hi> ſelves, by <hi>your</hi> ſelves (as it doth, without contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie conclude <hi>you</hi>) to have <hi>varyed, altered</hi> &amp; <hi>changed</hi> the <hi>Cauſe</hi> Point-blank, as <hi>I</hi> have charged upon <hi>ye,</hi> in <hi>this</hi> the <hi>chiefeſt</hi> and <hi>moſt</hi> weighty part of the <hi>Publick</hi> Intereſt, (the <hi>main</hi> ſubject of the <hi>Conteſt</hi>) in theſe words.</p>
            <p>Settlement, <hi>Pag.</hi> 29. Article 8. ye thus ſay, <hi>That the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatives have, and ſhall be underſtood to have the ſupreme Truſt, in order to the preſervation and government of the whole, and that their power extend, without the conſent or concurrence of any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Perſon; or Perſons; to the enacting and aboliſhing of Courts of Juſtice, and Publick Offices, and to the enacting, altering,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119149:6"/> repealing, and declaring of Laws; and the higheſt, and final Judgment in all natural or civil things; but not concerning things Spiritual or Evangelical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Than <hi>which,</hi> what can be more <hi>Emphatically,</hi> or more <hi>Peremto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily</hi> expreſt? And yet how have <hi>ye</hi> (in <hi>your</hi> late <hi>Humble Petition</hi> and <hi>Addreſs) pray'd</hi> the <hi>Parliament</hi> to <hi>take</hi> power, (which <hi>they</hi> have thereupon) yea, the <hi>Higheſt</hi> and <hi>Final Judgment,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>things Spiritual</hi> or <hi>Evangelical.</hi> viz. What of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of <hi>things Evangelical</hi> or <hi>Spiritual,</hi> ſhall be encouraged and protected, and what not: And <hi>this</hi> as (and upon) the <hi>Baſis</hi> of a <hi>Government</hi> of a <hi>Free-State</hi> (which deſtroys the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>it,</hi> even whilſt <hi>ye</hi> ſpake thereof) <hi>without a ſingle Perſon, King-ſhip, or houſe of Peers;</hi> (who have taken upon <hi>them</hi> (at <hi>your</hi> Preſcription) to be <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Lords</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> (for where <hi>any</hi> take upon <hi>them</hi> to <hi>preſcribe</hi> Laws, and <hi>finally</hi> to <hi>determine,</hi> what ſhall be, and what not) (as is done in the caſe, there ſuch aſſume <hi>Superiority</hi> or <hi>Lord-ſhip;</hi> this is irrefragable) <hi>I</hi> ſay, who have taken upon <hi>them,</hi> to be <hi>Kings</hi> &amp; <hi>Lords</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> of which <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> is made of <hi>God, Lord</hi> and <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>one</hi> (ſingle) and <hi>only Law-giver, who is able to ſave and to deſtroy;</hi> and hath ſaved <hi>you</hi> (and others by <hi>you</hi>) from <hi>thoſe</hi> who had, and would further have <hi>lorded</hi> it over <hi>your conſciences,</hi> (or have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed <hi>you</hi>) and hath deſtroyed <hi>them</hi> with a <hi>ſtroke reaching up to Heaven;</hi> yea, even by <hi>your</hi> hands; whoſe <hi>Lording</hi> Spirit over <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> (after <hi>all theſe</hi> Wars and Deſolations, and preſently upon <hi>your</hi> cry for <hi>your,</hi> and <hi>your</hi> Countries <hi>Religious Rights,</hi> (or <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi>) that there was <hi>but a ſtep</hi> (as ye cry out in <hi>your</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">See the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation, <hi>April 6. 1659.</hi>
               </note> Repreſentation) <hi>betwixt it and its Death,</hi> and the <hi>moſt</hi> notable <hi>Revolution</hi> thereupon, and <hi>Deliverance</hi>) hath entred into <hi>you,</hi> and from <hi>you</hi> into the <hi>Parliament,</hi> (into <hi>whom</hi> neither <hi>Swords,</hi> nor <hi>Plots,</hi> nor <hi>force,</hi> nor <hi>Powers</hi> of <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> could drive nor enter <hi>it</hi> before, nor ſubjugate thereunto; acting <hi>in</hi> and <hi>by,</hi> and <hi>through you</hi> and <hi>them,</hi> and ſeeking to bring to paſs, what <hi>it</hi> ſought before, but never could accompliſh againſt <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> but was ſtill (even to <hi>aſtoniſhment</hi> and <hi>wonder</hi>) daſht in pieces (as often as in <hi>any</hi> ſort of men, <hi>it</hi> ſought to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt <hi>it</hi>) by the <hi>Powerful</hi> preſence and <hi>Arme</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> in <hi>you</hi> and <hi>them,</hi> who will as certainly daſh you in pieces (in whom <hi>this</hi> Spirit ſo <hi>curſt</hi> of <hi>God</hi> before <hi>your</hi> eyes, and cut down by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119149:6"/> 
               <hi>you,</hi> is got, and acts, and lives) as <hi>it</hi> hath done <hi>all,</hi> of <hi>all</hi> ſorts in whom it got, liv'd and acted, againſt <hi>you;</hi> yea, with a <hi>heavy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> ſtroke, and <hi>more</hi> furions rebukes, becauſe, by <hi>you he</hi> hath executed <hi>his dreadful</hi> Judgments againſt <hi>ſuch,</hi> and delivered <hi>you</hi> from <hi>their</hi> cruelty and power, as oft as ye called upon <hi>him</hi> in ſincerity and truth, in the dayes of <hi>your</hi> diſtreſs; I ſay, <hi>ye</hi> will be <hi>Daſht</hi> in Peeces, <hi>except ye repent,</hi> the <hi>Mouth</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Hoſts</hi> hath ſpoken <hi>it,</hi> for <hi>he</hi> is come, and <hi>his</hi> day draweth nigh, wherein, <hi>for the Oppreſſion of the Poor, and the Sighing of the Needy; I will ariſe ſaith the Lord, and ſet him in ſafety, from him that puffeth at him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let the <hi>eye</hi> of <hi>honeſty</hi> be open in <hi>you,</hi> and with <hi>it</hi> ſee where <hi>ye</hi> are, and whereto <hi>your</hi> high Prieſt and Doctor, and <hi>his</hi> Brethren (through whom aroſe <hi>this</hi> ſmoak of the <hi>bottomleſs</hi> pit) hath led <hi>you,</hi> viz. to betray <hi>your</hi> principle the <hi>good Old Cauſe,</hi> as ſoon as <hi>ye</hi> are delivered; thereby endeavouring to haſten the <hi>vengeance</hi> of <hi>God</hi> upon <hi>your</hi> heads; For tell <hi>me,</hi> whether <hi>ye</hi> having <hi>thus changed</hi> the <hi>Cauſe</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> owned, <hi>ye</hi> can expect otherwiſe, than that the Lord ſhould diſ-own <hi>you,</hi> and change <hi>his</hi> hard towards <hi>you,</hi> viz. from <hi>that</hi> to <hi>you,</hi> as <hi>his</hi> friends; to <hi>that</hi> againſt <hi>you,</hi> as <hi>his</hi> enemies.</p>
            <p>Thus have <hi>I</hi> undenyably proved out of <hi>your</hi> own mouths, in <hi>your</hi> own plain &amp; expreſs words, that <hi>ye have changed the Cauſe, from that which ye at firſt, and all along engaged in and for, and declared even to that of your Enemies, againſt which ye engaged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here <hi>I</hi> might end, but being deſirous out of <hi>truth,</hi> of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Tender</hi> Compaſſion to <hi>you,</hi> (if by any means <hi>ye</hi> may ſee <hi>your</hi> error and be recovered, (as <hi>I</hi> ſaid) out of the <hi>Snare</hi> in which <hi>ye</hi> are taken;) <hi>I</hi> ſhall yet produce (for <hi>your</hi> further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction) ſome further paſſages of <hi>that your Settlement,</hi> againſt <hi>your Addreſs</hi> in the <hi>Caſe;</hi> yea, the <hi>very</hi> Article, out of which this <hi>New</hi> one would ſeem to be drawn, and unto it to allude, but is no more <hi>it,</hi> than an <hi>Harlot</hi> is a <hi>chaſt</hi> Spouſe, though <hi>it</hi> be got into the <hi>Bed</hi> of the <hi>Husband,</hi> and hath bedeckt <hi>it</hi> ſelf, with ſome of the <hi>Spouſes</hi> Apparrel, the better to deceive; as by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>other, I</hi> ſhall by and by, make to appear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Settlement,</hi> Pag. 24 Art. 9. <hi>Ye</hi> ſay, <hi>Concerning Religion we a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeas followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1 <hi>It is intended that Chriſtian Religion be held forth, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119149:7"/> recommended as the Publick Profeſſion of the Nation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> or the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Diſciples</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> never <hi>limited the holy one of Iſrael,</hi> as doth the <hi>Religion</hi> held forth in <hi>that your</hi> Article, but by the <hi>unlimited</hi> Spirit <hi>it</hi> teſtified againſt <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Worſhips,</hi> (whether <hi>ſuch</hi> as were commanded of <hi>God,</hi> and had their end, or not) <hi>I</hi> ſay, <hi>all</hi> the <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips</hi> of <hi>them,</hi> even in <hi>their times</hi> and <hi>places,</hi> who <hi>limited the holy one of Iſrael,</hi> as the <hi>Scriptures</hi> teſtifie; as alſo of the <hi>Beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Tumults, Stockings, Mockings, Whippings,</hi> and <hi>Impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonments,</hi> which <hi>ſuch</hi> received from <hi>thoſe</hi> who <hi>limited</hi> as it is at this day; and it is to be obſerved, that the word <hi>Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> is not to be found in this <hi>your new</hi> one, <hi>your new</hi> Article; nay, the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>it</hi> knew, that the very ſound of the name would quickly cauſe the vizor to be pluckt off, and that by it, (viz. the <hi>Chriſtian)</hi> the <hi>Hopocriſie</hi> of <hi>this Antichriſtian</hi> would be ſeen and diſcovered.</p>
            <p>Settlement. <hi>Which we deſire, may by the grace of God, be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the greateſt purity, in Doctrine, Worſhip and Diſcipline, according to the word of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Scriptures ye</hi> mean, where ſuch a <hi>Religion</hi> (as of <hi>Chriſt)</hi> is not to be found (but of <hi>Idolaters</hi> and <hi>Antichriſts)</hi> as <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits God, ſtints his witneſs, compels conſcience,</hi> (with <hi>outward</hi> force) and <hi>caſts all ſuch out of protection</hi> (as this <hi>your new</hi> one doth) even <hi>all</hi> thoſe who by the <hi>grace of God</hi> are inſtructed, and unto <hi>whom</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſpoken with a <hi>ſtrong hand,</hi> and <hi>inſtructed them, that they ſhould not walk in the way of this people,</hi> (the <hi>way</hi> of the <hi>falſe</hi> worſhips, and worſhippers of <hi>this</hi> Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, out of which <hi>they</hi> are come) but to <hi>reprove,</hi> and who have and muſt (if the <hi>Lord</hi> will yet ſtrive with <hi>this</hi> People) <hi>reprove</hi> and <hi>bear witneſs</hi> againſt <hi>them; I</hi> ſay, the <hi>Lord</hi> hath ſpoken to <hi>them,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Say ye not a confedereſie to all them, to whom this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall ſay a confedereſie, neither fear ye their fear, nor be afraid; ſanctifie the Lord of Hoſts himſelf, and let him be your fear, and let him be your dread; and he ſhall be a ſanctuary, but for a ſtone of Stumbling, and for a rock of offence, to both the Houſes of Iſrael; for a gin, and a ſnare to the inhabitants of Jeruſalem, and many among them, ſhall ſtumble and fall, and be broken, and be ſnared, and be taken.</hi> The <hi>word</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> it is to <hi>them,</hi> and to <hi>you,</hi> and as concerning <hi>you</hi> in this matter.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119149:7"/>
            <p>Settlement. <hi>The inſtructing of the People whereunto, in a publick way, (ſo it be not compulſive) as alſo the maintaining of able Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers for that end, &amp; for the confutation or diſcovery of Hereſy, Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, &amp; whatſoever is contrary to ſound Doctrine, is allowed to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for by our Repreſentatives. The maintainance of which Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, may be out of a publick Treaſury, and we deſire not by Tythes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>your New Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> there's not a <hi>word</hi> of this, (<hi>viz.) Able Teachers for the inſtructing of the People in a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick way, ſo it be not compulſive, the maintenance of able Teachers for that end, and for the confutation of Hereſie, Error, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is contrary to ſound Doctrine, the maintenance of which Teachers we deſire may not be by Tythes.</hi> And (as <hi>your</hi> Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to the <hi>ſaid</hi> Settlement, hath it, <hi>Pag.</hi> 28.) <hi>The taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of Tythes,</hi> (the <hi>Sore</hi> ſuffering of <hi>Gods</hi> Witneſſes, and the <hi>Life</hi> of that Miniſtry, which ſpeakes in <hi>You,</hi> and in the behalf of <hi>Its</hi> encouragement, countenance and maintaining) <hi>and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that maintenance which ſhall be thought competent for able Teachers to inſtruct the People, into ſome other way leſs ſubject to ſcruple and contention.</hi> I ſay, In your <hi>New Profeſſion,</hi> there's not a word of this; Nay the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>it</hi> likes not <hi>this</hi> language, <hi>it</hi> cannot ſpeake <hi>it,</hi> it's <hi>too pure,</hi> it's <hi>Death</hi> to <hi>it,</hi> it knows <hi>it</hi> not; 'Tis the voice of the <hi>chaſte</hi> Spouſe, not of the <hi>ſtrange</hi> Woman, the <hi>Harlot,</hi> whoſe <hi>bed</hi> is <hi>defiled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Settlement 2. <hi>That to the publick Profeſſion, ſo held forth, none be compelled by penalties or otherwiſe, but onely may be endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to be won by ſound Doctrine, and the example of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pure Language <hi>indeed,</hi> the <hi>voice</hi> of the <hi>Virgin,</hi> of <hi>You,</hi> in <hi>Your</hi> Virgin ſtate, but not of the <hi>Adultereſſe,</hi> of this <hi>Your adulterous</hi> ſtate, which compels by the <hi>high</hi> penalty of <hi>excluſion</hi> of <hi>Protection,</hi> to the <hi>Bed</hi> of <hi>whoredomes,</hi> out of which <hi>Protection</hi> it is caſt, as being <hi>too</hi> chaſte, and as <hi>Judging</hi> ſuch a <hi>Defilement.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:119149:8"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>Now followeth the <hi>ARTICLE</hi> it ſelf: See the <hi>COMPARISON.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="5">Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>That ſuch as Profeſſe Faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell rows="5">
                        <hi>Addreſs.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>That all perſons who profeſs Faith in God the Father, and in Jeſus Chriſt his eternal Son, and in the holy Ghoſt, God coequal with the Father &amp; the Son, God bleſſed for evermore,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>However differing in Judgement from the Doctrine, Worſhip and Diſcipline, publickly held forth as aforeſaid,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>And do acknowledge the holy Scriptures of the Old &amp; New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to be the reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or written Word or will of God,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ſhall not be reſtrained from, but ſhall be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected in the Profeſſion of their Faith, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Religion,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>ſhall not be reſtrained from their profeſſion, but have due encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement &amp; equal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection in the profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Faith, and exerciſe of Religion,</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>according to their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, in any place (except ſuch as ſhall be ſet apart for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip, where we provide not for them, unleſs they have leave)</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ſo they abuſe not this Liberty to the Civil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury of others, or to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall diſturbance of the publick Peace on their Parts.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>whilſt they abuſe not this Liberty to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil injury of others, or diſturbance of others in their way of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipps.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:119149:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Exceptions</hi> againſt <hi>this</hi> Article of <hi>Your New</hi> Faith.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That in the <hi>firſt</hi> part of it concerning God, the Tearms are <hi>more</hi> and <hi>different.</hi> That (<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Settlement</hi>) hath onely theſe, <hi>viz. That ſuch as profeſſe Faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> (words few and ſimple) The Addreſſe, <hi>That all perſons who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe Faith in God the Father, and in Jeſus Chriſt his eternall Son, the true God, and in the holy Spirit, God coequall with the Father and the Son, One God bleſſed for ever.</hi> Which becauſe <hi>they</hi> are not (<hi>all</hi> of <hi>them</hi>) the words of <hi>Scripture,</hi> (for where ſaith it, <hi>God coequall with the Father &amp; the Son?</hi> And for that <hi>thoſe</hi> of <hi>them</hi> which are <hi>Scripture</hi> words, are no where ſpoken by the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> ſo together as <hi>Ye</hi> have ſet them, nor for that purpoſe, <hi>viz.</hi> to hold forth a <hi>Diſtinction</hi> of <hi>Perſons,</hi> of <hi>three</hi> Perſons in the <hi>Godhead</hi> or <hi>Trinity,</hi> which the Imagination of Man hath formed of <hi>God,</hi> which knowes not <hi>God;</hi> And in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard theſe <hi>Your</hi> Tearms are laid as ſo many <hi>Shibboleths</hi> or <hi>Snares</hi> for the <hi>tender Conſciences</hi> of <hi>thoſe</hi> who cannot ſpeak of <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>will</hi> and <hi>words</hi> that <hi>Mans</hi> wiſdome teacheth (which muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded) but in the <hi>will</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>words</hi> which the <hi>holy Ghoſt teacheth.</hi> And, foraſmuch as <hi>ye</hi> are, notwithſtanding ſo <hi>Dogmaticall</hi> and <hi>peremptory</hi> therein, as that <hi>ye</hi> make the <hi>Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> of this <hi>your</hi> Faith, to be the <hi>Quallification, ſine qua non,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which there is no <hi>Protection;</hi> And have placed it as the <hi>bound</hi> or <hi>limit</hi> of <hi>Conſcience-Liberty,</hi> under which <hi>it</hi> muſt come or ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, (which indeed, deſtroyes <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> for where it is <hi>bound</hi> in any one Particular, there it cannot be ſaid to be <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi>) And inaſmuch as <hi>Ye</hi> ſeem to ſet ſuch a <hi>high</hi> value on the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> that <hi>ye</hi> make the acknowledging of what <hi>ye</hi> have pleaſed to call it (though not in <hi>its own</hi> words, nor have <hi>ye</hi> made it to appear that it ſaith ſo of <hi>it</hi> ſelf) <hi>eſſentiall</hi> to <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> (of which in the next particular) And finally in that <hi>ye</hi> exact <hi>this</hi> Profeſſion as the <hi>iſſue</hi> and <hi>fruit</hi> of <hi>all</hi> the <hi>bloud</hi> and <hi>Warrs,</hi> and <hi>your</hi> late <hi>Deliverance. I</hi> ſay, upon theſe Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, in the <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>dread</hi> of the <hi>Eternall God,</hi> I do require <hi>you,</hi> and all <hi>your</hi> Doctors, and both <hi>their</hi> Mothers, the <hi>two</hi> Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, and <hi>all</hi> their Children the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> to prove, in <hi>Plain</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:119149:9"/> and <hi>expreſſe</hi> Scripture words together, <hi>where the Scriptures do attribute Faith or believing, to the holy Spirit as a diſtinct Perſon,</hi> as here <hi>ye</hi> have ſet it, Or, confeſſe that <hi>ye</hi> cannot, and ſo raze out with <hi>your</hi> own Pens, <hi>your new Confeſſion</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> contained in <hi>this</hi> Article, which <hi>ye</hi> ſeek to enforce as the <hi>fruit</hi> and <hi>iſſue</hi> of <hi>all,</hi> and with <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>Penalty;</hi> Or, if <hi>ye</hi> are ſilent, <hi>ye</hi> ſhall be taken <hi>pro confeſſo,</hi> that is to ſay, by <hi>your</hi> ſilence to confeſſe, that <hi>ye</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. True it is, the <hi>Scriptures</hi> bear Record of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that he ſaid to his <hi>Diſciples, Ye believe in God, believe alſo in me,</hi> John 14. 1. And, <hi>He that believeth in me, as the Scripture hath ſaid, out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of living water, this ſpake he of the holy Spirit, which they that believe on him [ſhould] receive, for the holy Ghoſt was [not yet] given, becauſe that Jeſus was not yet glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified,</hi> John 7. 39. And <hi>no man knoweth the Father but the Son, and he to whomſoever the Son will reveal him. The Comforter, when he is come, even the Spirit of Truth, which proceedeth from the Father, he ſhall teſtifie of me,</hi> John 15. 25, 26. And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid unto <hi>them</hi> at <hi>Epheſus, Have ye received the holy Ghoſt ſince ye believed? And they ſaid unto him [we have not ſo much as heard whether there be any holy Ghoſt] And when Paul had laid his hands on them, [the holy Ghoſt came on them]</hi> Act. 19. 1, 2, 6. And again, <hi>In whom alſo, [after] ye believed, ye were ſealed with the holy Spirit of promiſe,</hi> Epheſ. 1. 13. And, <hi>There are three that bear record in heaven, the Father, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one. And there are three that bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe on earth, the Spirit, the Water, and the Bloud, and theſe three agree in one,</hi> 1 John 5. 7, 8. And this we believe and ſet our ſeals to. But where ſay <hi>they</hi> as <hi>ye</hi> have exacted it? Now the <hi>words</hi> of <hi>Mans</hi> wiſdom concerning <hi>God,</hi> which knowes not <hi>God,</hi> which muſt be confounded, which muſt be brought to nought, which the <hi>holy Ghoſt teacheth not,</hi> and the <hi>Doctrines</hi> which are not from the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Truth, we</hi> reject.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> that the words, <hi>viz. And do acknowledge the holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament, to be the revealed, or written word or will of God.</hi> Are wholly added as ſo many <hi>Shibboleths or ſnares,</hi> alſo for <hi>thoſe</hi> who in <hi>tenderneſs</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience</hi> to <hi>God</hi> cannot ſay of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> what they ſay not in <hi>their</hi> own words of <hi>themſelves.</hi> And that <hi>there be</hi> who in <hi>tenderneſs</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> to <hi>God</hi> cannot do <hi>thus,</hi> is known by the <hi>ſufferings</hi> of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119149:9"/> 
                  <hi>many</hi> in <hi>divers</hi> parts of the <hi>Nation,</hi> becauſe of <hi>it.</hi> True it is, the <hi>Scriptures</hi> ſay of <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> that <hi>in the beginning was the word, and the word was with God, and the word was God, the ſame was in the beginning with God; All things were made by him, and without him was not any thing made that was made. And the word was made fleſh and dwelt amongſt us, and we beheld his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry as the glory of the only begotten ſon of the Father, full of grace and truth,</hi> John 1. 3, 14. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pholding all things by the word of his power,</hi> Heb. 1. 3. <hi>His name is called the word of God, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords,</hi> Revel. 19. 13, 16. And of this <hi>Word</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> are a <hi>true</hi> declaration, Luke 1. 1. And <hi>all Scriptures is given by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for Doctrine, for reproofe, for correction, for inſtruction in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, that the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all good words,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 16. And <hi>the Propheſie came not in old time by the will of man, but holy men of God, ſpake as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt.</hi> 2 Pet. 1. 20, 21. And <hi>this</hi> the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſaith of <hi>it</hi> ſelf, and this <hi>we</hi> own and teſtifie, and <hi>our</hi> Teſtimony is true, but as for the terms <hi>revealed, or written word, or will of God,</hi> where ſayes the <hi>Scripture ſuch words; I</hi> require <hi>you</hi> and <hi>your</hi> Doctors again, to prove <hi>it,</hi> for <hi>we</hi> cannot take a teſtimony of the <hi>Scripures,</hi> which is not from the <hi>Spirit</hi> that gave <hi>it,</hi> which ſpake <hi>its</hi> own <hi>words,</hi> and <hi>its</hi> words <hi>we</hi> receive, who have received the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which cannot be <hi>impoſed</hi> upon by the <hi>wiſdome</hi> of <hi>man, which muſt be confounded.</hi> 'Tis ſtrange, and a thing to be noted, that <hi>ye, your Prieſts and Doctors,</hi> who keep ſuch adoe about the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and who have put <hi>you</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this, and ſo magnifie the <hi>Letter,</hi> cannot make <hi>four</hi> lines of a <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of <hi>your faith,</hi> in the <hi>Letter</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures</hi> (as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by this <hi>your</hi> Article) and that <hi>thoſe</hi> whom <hi>ye</hi> ſeek to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare with <hi>terms</hi> about the <hi>Letter,</hi> which <hi>it</hi> ſaith not of <hi>it</hi> ſelf, and whom <hi>ye</hi> judge (but unrighteouſly) as undervaluing of the <hi>Letter,</hi> and as not attributing <hi>that</hi> to <hi>it</hi> which <hi>ye</hi> would have; yea, as denying <hi>it,</hi> and therefore have made <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>proviſion,</hi> ſhould be conſtrained by <hi>your</hi> going from the <hi>Letter,</hi> (whileſt <hi>ye</hi> are making the confeſſion of <hi>your faith</hi> in the <hi>Letter,</hi> and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>that your confeſſion</hi> up for <hi>all</hi> to worſhip <hi>your</hi> Image of the <hi>Letter; I</hi> ſay, that <hi>they</hi> ſhould be conſtrained, or that <hi>ye</hi> ſhould give them this juſt occaſion, to Judge <hi>you</hi> for departing from the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119149:10"/> 
                  <hi>Letter,</hi> whoſe Judgment <hi>ye</hi> cannot avoid, for that it is the Judgment wherewith (by <hi>this your proviſion) ye</hi> Judge, and ſo <hi>thou art inexcuſable O man, who judgeſt another, and yet doeſt the ſame thing, for in ſo doing thou condemneſt thy ſelf.</hi> And is it not alſo a <hi>ſtrange</hi> thing, for <hi>any</hi> to be ſo deluded by the <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> as to believe that <hi>thoſe</hi> who witneſs the <hi>holy Spirit</hi> which ſpake in <hi>them,</hi> who ſpake forth the <hi>Scriptures, as they were moved of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and who by the <hi>Revelation</hi> of the ſame <hi>Spirit,</hi> that moved in <hi>them</hi> who ſpake forth the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> know <hi>it</hi> to be <hi>true,</hi> and witneſs <hi>it</hi> to be <hi>fulfilled,</hi> and <hi>fulfilling</hi> in <hi>them</hi> (as do the <hi>people</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> who are aimed at in this <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion) I</hi> ſay, to beleeve that <hi>ſuch</hi> are denyers of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and that <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>ſnare,</hi> and in <hi>ſuch</hi> terms ſhould be laid for <hi>them,</hi> as <hi>ſuch,</hi> as in <hi>this</hi> Article, ſurely <hi>they</hi> can as ſoon deny <hi>their</hi> life, the <hi>holy Spirit</hi> in <hi>them,</hi> as the <hi>words it</hi> ſpake forth.</p>
               <p>But to <hi>your</hi> terms, <hi>the revealed or written word, or will of God.</hi> How can <hi>any</hi> thing be called or ſaid by the creature to be the <hi>will</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> but what is <hi>Gods</hi> diſcovery of <hi>himſelf,</hi> or <hi>Revelation</hi> to the Creature; otherwiſe, who can attribute or ſay any ſuch thing of <hi>God,</hi> as <hi>his</hi> will, ſeeing that <hi>he</hi> is <hi>infinite,</hi> and cannot otherwiſe than by the <hi>Revelation</hi> of <hi>himſelf,</hi> and the language of <hi>his</hi> Spirit, in the meaſure of himſelf be comprehended or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt. How is it then, and from whence comes it, that <hi>ye</hi> thus diſtinguiſh, <hi>the Revealed will of God,</hi> which implies ſomething elſe, that is or may be called by the Creature, the <hi>will</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which cannot be affirmed, ſo <hi>intruding into thoſe things, which ye have not ſeen, in a voluntary humility, and worſhipping of the Scriptures, into which ye are beguiled, and of your reward</hi> (for <hi>your</hi> former ſervice to the <hi>Nations</hi> Liberty) <hi>by the ſubtilty of men, which have lain in wait to deceive you, vainly puft up with their fleſhly mind, &amp; not holding the head, from which all the body by joynts, and bands, having nouriſhment Miniſtred, and knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, encreaſeth with the encreaſe of God.</hi> How ſoon do <hi>ye</hi> appear by <hi>this</hi> to be <hi>ſunck</hi> in the <hi>Ground</hi> of <hi>your</hi> Divinity (which <hi>ye</hi> lay as a foundation for <hi>all</hi> to build upon, as a <hi>God</hi> for <hi>all</hi> to worſhip) whileſt ye are ſoaring aloft to ſpeak that of <hi>God,</hi> which <hi>ye</hi> do not underſtand, to diſtinguiſh of <hi>Gods will,</hi> who is undiſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhable? And ſo (<hi>Friends</hi>) how ſoon is <hi>Babel</hi> writ upon <hi>your</hi> goodly buildings? How quickly is <hi>your</hi> language confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119149:10"/> lifting <hi>it</hi> ſelf up (indeed) to Heaven, but is thus brought down to Hell. Ceaſe, <hi>vain man,</hi> whoſe breath is in <hi>thy</hi> noſtrils, to take upon <hi>thee,</hi> to ſpeak of <hi>Gods</hi> ſecret, for wherein art <hi>thou</hi> to be accounted of, ceaſe <hi>ye</hi> potſherds of the earth, to preſcribe to <hi>conſcience,</hi> as to the <hi>things</hi> and worſhip of <hi>God;</hi> of which only <hi>he</hi> is <hi>Lord, leaſt he daſh you to peeces.</hi> Come down to the <hi>door,</hi> the <hi>witneſs</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>you,</hi> the <hi>little</hi> thing that is <hi>as a grain of Muſtard-ſeed,</hi> to that which reproves (the <hi>Dominion</hi> of <hi>God</hi>) to that which <hi>makes manifeſt,</hi> (the <hi>Light</hi> which comes from the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Saviour</hi> of <hi>all</hi> them who believe in <hi>him</hi>) leaſt <hi>ye</hi> be turned out amongſt the <hi>Beaſts</hi> of the <hi>Field, and times paſs over you,</hi> till <hi>ye</hi> acknowledge that <hi>the moſt high ruleth among the children of men,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> alone, is as of <hi>right, Lord</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Again,</hi> as to the <hi>things</hi> of <hi>God revealed</hi> on record in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of <hi>truth. Can any man ſay, that Jeſus is the Lord, but by the Holy Ghoſt?</hi> Is it not thus written, can any man ſay, that <hi>all Scriptures is given by inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> but by the <hi>Revelation</hi> of the <hi>ſame</hi> Spirit, which <hi>inſpired</hi> the <hi>holy men</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> who ſpake and wrote as <hi>they</hi> were <hi>moved</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt?</hi> Knows any man <hi>the things of God, but the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God;</hi> and <hi>they</hi> who have <hi>received the Spirit, that is not the Spirit of the World, but the Spirit which is of God; that they may know the things that are freely given them of God?</hi> And are not the <hi>Scriptures</hi> the <hi>things</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>things freely given of God, the deep things of God,</hi> which <hi>none</hi> but the <hi>Spirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veales,</hi> none but the <hi>Spirit ſearcheth out? Now the Lord is that Spirit, and where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> Are <hi>they</hi> not a <hi>Book ſealed,</hi> and is not the <hi>viſion</hi> of <hi>all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to all,</hi> (who have not received the <hi>Spirit) as a book ſealed, which men deliver to one that is learned, ſaying, Read this I pray thee, and he ſaith I cannot, for it is Sealed; and the Book is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to him that is not learned, and he ſaith, I am not learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi> Is it not <hi>thus</hi> written, yea; Is it not alſo written? <hi>Bind up the Teſtimony and Seale the Law among the Diſciples,</hi> (thoſe who have received the <hi>Spirit</hi>) yea; ſaith not <hi>Chriſt Jeſus, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I thank thee, becauſe that thou haſt hid theſe things, from the wiſe, and prudent, and haſt revealed them to Babes, even ſo, Father, for ſo it ſeemeth good in thy ſight?</hi> And ſaid <hi>he</hi> not to <hi>his</hi> Diſciples? <hi>to you it is given to know the myſteries of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119149:11"/> Kingome of Heaven, but to them it is not given, therefore ſpeak I to them in Parables, becauſe they ſeeing, ſee not, and hearing they hear not, neither do they underſtand. And in them is fulfilled that of Iſa.</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>thoſe</hi> were the <hi>Jewes,</hi> of whom it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that <hi>they that dwell at Jeruſalem, and their rulers, becauſe they knew him not, nor yet the voices of the Prophets, which are read every Sabbath day; they have fulfilled them in condemning him.</hi> How then can <hi>any</hi> man <hi>know</hi> of a <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>acknowledge</hi> them to be the <hi>revealed word or will of God,</hi> but by <hi>Revelation,</hi> the <hi>Revelation</hi> of the <hi>ſame Spirit</hi> as moved <hi>them</hi> who wrote <hi>it</hi> to ſpeak it forth, and if <hi>it</hi> cannot be of a truth acknowledged to be ſuch, but by <hi>Revelation,</hi> how is it then that <hi>ye</hi> require all to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge <hi>it</hi> to be the <hi>revealed word or will of God,</hi> without hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſpect to the <hi>Spirit,</hi> or to <hi>Revelation?</hi> What <hi>faith</hi> is this that <hi>ye impoſe</hi> upon <hi>all</hi> People, to confeſs upon pain of being denyed <hi>protection,</hi> whether <hi>they</hi> have received the <hi>Spirit</hi> or not? which <hi>Spirit</hi> unleſs <hi>they</hi> have received and by <hi>it</hi> ſpeak, <hi>they</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not acknowledg <hi>it</hi> to be ſuch without a <hi>lye</hi> againſt the <hi>truth?</hi> What a <hi>Religion</hi> have <hi>ye</hi> here held forth? that ſaith, <hi>Profeſs ſo and ſo, of God, Chriſt, the Spirit, whether thou of a truth, know them to be ſo or no? And acknowledge the Scriptures to be ſo and ſo, whether they ſay ſo of themſelves, or of God, Chriſt, the Spirit, or that thou underſtandeſt them by the Spirit to be ſo or not, or thou ſhalt be caſt out;</hi> What a <hi>cruelty</hi> is in <hi>this</hi> Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that requires a man to profeſs what he knows not, nor can without another, viz. the <hi>Spirit,</hi> (as <hi>I</hi> have proved) and the <hi>gift</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt cannot be bought with money,</hi> nor can <hi>it</hi> be <hi>forced</hi>) or excludes <hi>him</hi> the benefit of the <hi>Law,</hi> the <hi>priviledge</hi> of <hi>his Birth-right</hi> (how <hi>diſerving</hi> ſoever he be as to the <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or howmuch ſoever <hi>he</hi> hath <hi>fought,</hi> or <hi>ſuffered,</hi> or <hi>done,</hi> for <hi>Liberty,</hi> for <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience, Liberty Civil</hi> and <hi>Religious,</hi> or exerciſes a <hi>good Conſcience</hi> towards <hi>God</hi> or <hi>Man,</hi> or is ſerviceable in <hi>his</hi> Generation, or according to <hi>Scripture</hi> in <hi>his</hi> profeſſion; or knows the <hi>Lord,</hi> or fears before <hi>him,</hi> or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe) ſo that if <hi>he</hi> profeſs what <hi>ye</hi> ſay, and not by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which (as hath been made appear) <hi>ye</hi> have not reſpect to, for <hi>ye</hi> require it of <hi>all</hi> that mind <hi>your</hi> protection, and <hi>all</hi> have not the <hi>Spirit) he</hi> lyes, and ſo <hi>ye</hi> expoſe him to the danger of the <hi>Lake</hi> that <hi>burnes with fire and brimſtone,</hi> as it is written, <hi>and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119149:11"/> all Lyars are for the Lake,</hi> if <hi>he</hi> do not profeſs <hi>it he</hi> is in danger of being caſt into the Pit, for preſerve <hi>him</hi> out of it, ye ſay, <hi>ye</hi> will not, in ſaying <hi>ſuch</hi> ſhall not be <hi>protected;</hi> That is to ſay, in <hi>plain</hi> Engliſh, <hi>Profeſs of God, and Chriſt, and the Spirit, and acknowledge of the Scriptures what we will have thee, and ſay, thou ſhalt whether thou canſt, or not, whether thou haſt the Spirit and by it canſt ſpeak, or otherwiſe;</hi> Or, <hi>Do who will, what they will with thee in thy Profeſſion:</hi> And ſo <hi>ye</hi> expoſe <hi>him</hi> to be undone, either in <hi>Soul</hi> or <hi>Body,</hi> or both: Time was, it was otherwiſe with <hi>you</hi> (O <hi>my Friends,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> knew it) yea, it was <hi>your</hi> caſe, from <hi>your</hi> (then) and the <hi>Enemies</hi> of <hi>all</hi> who were againſt the <hi>enſlav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi> But now, alas! How ſoon hath night over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken <hi>ye?</hi> and Darkneſs covered <hi>ye?</hi> Wherein differs this <hi>your Profeſſion</hi> from that of the world? This <hi>Impoſition,</hi> in the root, from that of <hi>Rome,</hi> unto whoſe height of <hi>Coertion</hi> and <hi>cruelty,</hi> it will (in time) aſcend, if not beyond, unleſs <hi>it</hi> be cut down.</p>
               <p>Thus much for your Terms, <hi>Revealed or written Will of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now for the other, viz. <hi>Revealed</hi> or <hi>written Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is not a <hi>word</hi> a <hi>Revelation</hi> (truly, and ſo underſtood) in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priety of ſpeech? How is it then, that <hi>your</hi> Doctors cannot yet ſpeak of their believing, without a <hi>hereſie</hi> in proper ſpeaking? A <hi>Revealed Word,</hi> as much as to ſay, a <hi>written writing,</hi> a <hi>ſpoken ſpeech.</hi> Do <hi>they</hi> not call ſuch Improprieties, as theſe, <hi>Bulls,</hi> at <hi>Oxford?</hi> And diſdaine <hi>they</hi> not thoſe who ſpeak ſo, as the <hi>Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar</hi> or <hi>Ignorant?</hi> Deſerve they not then to be turned back again from <hi>their</hi> Doctorſhip of Divinity, in things concerning <hi>God,</hi> or being <hi>Teachers of others</hi> (unto which <hi>they</hi> pretend) to learn the Art of proper ſpeaking unto men? May not this be brought as a juſt reproofe and a Taunt, upon <hi>thoſe</hi> who have deſpiſed <hi>Truth,</hi> becauſe it hath been brought forth by a <hi>ſtammering tongue,</hi> as to <hi>Natural</hi> learning, viz. <hi>Has not the Head of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity, yet attained the Tongue of the learned?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Revealed Word of God, <hi>ſay ye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here <hi>ye</hi> are taken, as in the <hi>former;</hi> For, in that <hi>ye</hi> ſay, the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed Word of God,</hi> what do <hi>ye</hi> thereby imply, but that there is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119149:12"/> another <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God?</hi> Now <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Gods</hi> Revelation of himſelf to the Creature, and further than this the Creature cannot go, nor look, nor ſay, as to the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> For, as <hi>I</hi> ſaid, <hi>God</hi> is <hi>infinite</hi> and cannot be comprehended, nor un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, but in the Declaration of himſelf, <hi>Chriſt</hi> the <hi>Word;</hi> Nor to, or of this, can the Creature go or ſay, but by <hi>Revelation;</hi> For, ſaith <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God, All things are delivered me of my Father, and no man knoweth the Son but the Father, neither knoweth any man the Father ſave the Son, and he to whomſoever the Son will reveal him: The Comforter, when he is come, whom I will ſend to you from the Father, he ſhall teſtifie of me.</hi> Now to ſay, there are <hi>two Words</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> or to diſtinguiſh of the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> that <hi>one</hi> part of the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> is ſo, and <hi>another</hi> part is not ſo, (as <hi>ye</hi> muſt needs be underſtood to imply in the caſe) what is it, but to ſay, there are <hi>two Chriſts,</hi> or that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is divided, who neither is, nor can be; Than which, what can be more <hi>Blaſphemous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, for your Terms, <hi>Written Word of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How can, or dare any to ſay, without the <hi>higheſt</hi> Blaſphemy, that the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> or <hi>any viſible, comprehenſible</hi> thing, is the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> who is <hi>inviſible, incomprehenſible, whom no man hath ſeen, nor can ſee, God bleſſed for ever,</hi> who cannot be written, and <hi>his</hi> word is like <hi>himſelf;</hi> for when <hi>ye</hi> ſpeak of a <hi>written word</hi> of <hi>God, yee</hi> ſpeak of ſomething that is <hi>circumſcribed, Phyſical,</hi> or <hi>Local,</hi> that is to ſay, ſomething that may be ſeen, toucht, or han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled by Man, as Man, which <hi>God</hi> cannot be, nor <hi>his word,</hi> nor <hi>his will,</hi> (which is <hi>himſelf</hi>) nor <hi>his Church</hi> (which is <hi>in himſelf) the Ground and Pillar of truth.</hi> For, though <hi>God,</hi> from the beginning hath <hi>not left himſelf without a witneſs,</hi> but hath placed ſome thing of <hi>himſelf</hi> in Man (which <hi>reproves,</hi> which <hi>makes manifeſt,</hi> the <hi>Light</hi> which comes from <hi>Chriſt</hi>) to which <hi>he</hi> hath ſpoken through <hi>all</hi> generations, and declared <hi>his</hi> will ſo far as concerned <hi>that</hi> generation, to which <hi>he</hi> ſpake, as after divers other manners, ſo by <hi>writing,</hi> of which the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of <hi>truth</hi> (now extant) are a part, and but a part of what was ſo written, as the <hi>Scriptures</hi> themſelves teſtifie) yet to ſay of <hi>all</hi> that hath been ſo ſpoken, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared and wrote, from the beginning hitherto, that it is the <hi>word</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:119149:12"/> or <hi>will</hi> of <hi>God</hi> (which is <hi>unfathomable, incomprehenſible, unutter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, inexpreſſible</hi>) much leſs of the <hi>Scriptures</hi> (which are but a <hi>part</hi> of what was ſo written as aforeſaid) to ſay, that <hi>that</hi> is the <hi>written word</hi> or <hi>will</hi> of <hi>God</hi> (which the <hi>Scriptures</hi> no where ſay of themſelves) is as <hi>abſurd</hi> as <hi>Blaſphemous,</hi> and can no more be ſaid to be the <hi>written word</hi> or <hi>will</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> becauſe they are a <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of the <hi>will</hi> of <hi>God</hi> to many generations, or a <hi>Record</hi> in <hi>wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> with Pen, and Ink, of <hi>his word</hi> ſo ſpoken, by which <hi>his will</hi> was ſo declared to <hi>thoſe</hi> Generations; Or becauſe they being ſo recorded, are a Teſtimony, that <hi>God</hi> left not himſelf throughout all ages <hi>without a witneſs,</hi> nor <hi>his</hi> people, and ſo are <hi>uſeful</hi> for the <hi>Man</hi> of <hi>God</hi> (as the <hi>Spirit</hi> teſtifies in them) and were written for <hi>our</hi> learning (the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God</hi> (to which the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> in Paul ſpake) which <hi>is in God</hi>) than the <hi>Heavens</hi> can be ſaid to be the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> which were <hi>made,</hi> and are <hi>upholden</hi> by the <hi>word</hi> of his <hi>Power;</hi> for they <hi>declare the glory of God;</hi> Or, the <hi>Firmament,</hi> for <hi>it ſheweth his handy work:</hi> Or the day, for <hi>day by day, uttereth ſpeech;</hi> or the <hi>night,</hi> for <hi>night unto night ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth knowledge; or all</hi> of <hi>them,</hi> for <hi>there is no ſpeech, nor Language, where their voice is not heard: their line is gone out through all the Earth, and their words to the end of the world,</hi> which cannot be ſaid of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> this the <hi>Scriptures</hi> teſtifie, yea, even that <hi>the inviſible things of him from the Creation of the world, are clearly ſeen, being underſtood by the things that are made, even his eternal power and Godhead, ſo that they are</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> in <hi>Paul,</hi> of thoſe who <hi>held the Truth in unrighteouſneſs, becauſe that which is to be known of God, is manifeſt in them,</hi> for <hi>God hath ſhewn it to them) without excuſe,</hi> yea, that <hi>he left not himſelf without a witneſs, in that he did good,</hi> and <hi>gave us rain from Heaven and fruitful ſeaſons, filling our hearts with food and gladneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet, <hi>how do ye darken Counſel</hi> by <hi>words without knowledge,</hi> (words which neither the <hi>Scriptures</hi> know, nor the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> nor do <hi>ye your</hi> ſelves underſtand what <hi>ye</hi> ſay) and then ſet it up as the <hi>Faith of Gods Elect,</hi> to be <hi>impoſed</hi> upon <hi>all,</hi> yea, upon <hi>Gods Elect;</hi> yea, for a <hi>Snare</hi> for <hi>Gods Elect;</hi> whoſe <hi>Faith</hi> never ſought to inforce <hi>it</hi> ſelf, otherwiſe upon any, than by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending <hi>it</hi> ſelf to <hi>that of God in every mans Conſcience,</hi> which this of <hi>yours</hi> doth (viz. by the <hi>Penalty</hi> of excluſion of <hi>Protection,</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:119149:13"/> if it be not <hi>Profeſſed,</hi> and therefore <hi>we</hi> rejct it; and ſhould, though it were in the very words of Truth (which this of <hi>yours</hi> is not) becauſe <hi>coertion</hi> in <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> or <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in things <hi>Spiritual</hi> or <hi>Evangelical,</hi> we are ſure is out of <hi>Truth,</hi> and comes from <hi>him</hi> who is <hi>out of it,</hi> to wit, the Devil: O <hi>how would vain man be wiſe,</hi> in his wiſdom, to ſpeak of <hi>God, who by wiſdome knows not God,</hi> for ſo <hi>it hath pleaſed the wiſdom of God? But man is born as the wild Aſſes colt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude this particular; How can <hi>he</hi> be written who is <hi>without beginning of Dayes, or end of life?</hi> of whom it is written, <hi>who can declare his generation?</hi> How can <hi>he</hi> be ſaid to be written, who is the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> (and there is no other) without circumſcribing him, without making him an Image, a thing like unto <hi>your</hi> ſelves?</p>
               <p>The <hi>third Exception</hi> againſt this 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. Article of <hi>your</hi> Addreſs, is, that inſtead of the words, <hi>however differing in judgment from the Doctrine, Worſhip, or Diſcipline publickly held forth as aforeſaid,</hi> (viz. Article 1. where <hi>ye</hi> ſay, <hi>it is intended that Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion be held forth, and recommended, as the publick Profeſſion in this Nation (which we deſire may, by the grace of God be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to the greateſt purity, in Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the word of God, the inſtructing of the people whereunto, in a publick way (ſo it be not compulſive) as alſo the maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of able Teachers for that end, and for the confutation and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of hereſie, error,</hi> &amp; <hi>whatſoever is contrary to ſound Doctrine, is allowed to be provided for, by our Repreſentatives, the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of which Teachers may be out of a publick Treaſure, and we deſire not by Tythes.</hi> And <hi>Article 2. That to the publick Profeſſion ſo held forth, none be compelled, by Penalties or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, but onely may be endeavoured to be won by ſound Doctrine, and the example of a good Converſation.</hi> Which are the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate preceding Articles to this <hi>third;</hi> of either of which Articles, there is not a whiſper in this <hi>your new</hi> Profeſſion; <hi>I</hi> ſay, the <hi>third</hi> Exception is, that inſtead of the words, <hi>however differing in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, publickly held forth, as aforeſaid) ſhall not be reſtrained from, but ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected in the Profeſſion of their Faith, and exerciſe of Religion, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Conſciences;</hi> Theſe only are inſerted, viz. <hi>Shall not be reſtrained from their Profeſſion, but have due encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119149:13"/> and equal Protection, in the Profeſſion of their Faith, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of their Religion,</hi> which varies the caſe, both as to the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of the <hi>third</hi> Artitle of <hi>your</hi> ſaid <hi>Settlement,</hi> and <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and plainly ſhews, that the allowance of the Profeſſion of <hi>their</hi> faith, and the exerciſe of the Religion of <hi>ſuch as Profeſs faith in God by Jeſus Chriſt, according to their Conſciences (however differing in judgment from the Doctrine, Worſhip, or Diſcipline, publickly held forth,</hi> is not intended in <hi>this</hi> Article, nay its <hi>clear</hi> cut out; but the <hi>forcing</hi> of the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of <hi>all</hi> ſuch as ſhall differ in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from that which <hi>it</hi> holds forth as the <hi>Publick</hi> Profeſſion, which quite overthrows <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi> And it is worthy the obſervation, that the Clauſes, viz. <hi>However differing in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, from the Doctrine, Worſhip, or Diſcipline publickly held forth,</hi> and <hi>according to their Conſciences;</hi> are wholly left out of this <hi>ſixth</hi> Article of <hi>your</hi> Addreſs; it is the whole <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>words</hi> of the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>ſecond</hi> Article of <hi>your</hi> Settlement, aforeſaid, unto which <hi>theſe</hi> Clauſes of the <hi>third</hi> have relation.</p>
               <p>Which undenyably manifeſts, that as there is not a word of <hi>Conſcience</hi> in this <hi>your new</hi> Cauſe and profeſſion of Religion, ſo that it proceeds from the <hi>Spirit,</hi> not that which fought for, but that which fought againſt: and hath <hi>murthered Liberty</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> And further, that the <hi>good old Cauſe</hi> is <hi>changed,</hi> and that the hand hath done <hi>it</hi> which engaged againſt <hi>it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The <hi>fourth</hi> Exception is, that whereas in <hi>your</hi> Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Article 3. <hi>ye</hi> ſay, <hi>ſhall not be reſtrained from,</hi> (viz. ſuch as profeſs <hi>Faith</hi> in God by Jeſus Chriſt) <hi>but ſhall be protected in the profeſſion of their faith, and exerciſe of Religion, according to their Conſciences in any place (except ſuch as ſhall be ſet apart for the Publick Worſhip, where we provide not for them, except they have leave</hi>) This Article of <hi>your</hi> Addreſs runs it thus; <hi>ſhall not be reſtrained from,</hi> (viz. All perſons, who profeſs faith in God the Father, and in Jeſus Chriſt, &amp;c.) <hi>their profeſſion, but have due encouragement and equal protection;</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>ſuch</hi> only ſhall ſo have, as are of the <hi>ſame</hi> Profeſſion, as is therein publickly held forth, which indeed, is no <hi>encouragement</hi> at all, nor <hi>Protection</hi> of <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> but a <hi>meer</hi> deluſion, as ſeeming to hold forth that which <hi>it</hi> contains not, neither doth <hi>it</hi> intend, for (as <hi>I</hi> ſaid before, in the <hi>former</hi> exception (the Proviſions, viz. <hi>How<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ever differing in judgment from the Doctrine,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Publickly held
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119149:14"/> forth,</hi> &amp;c. And <hi>according to their Conſciences,</hi> and the Proviſion mentioned in this Exception, viz. <hi>In any place,</hi> &amp;c. (<hi>Except ſuch as ſhall be ſet apart for the Publick, &amp;c.</hi>) are wholly left out: And ſo the words, <hi>ſhall not be reſtrained from their Publike Profeſſion, but have due encouragement and equal Protection in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of their Faith, and exerciſe of Religion,</hi> muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily refer onely, (&amp; be ſo underſtood) unto thoſe of <hi>your</hi> own profeſſion, thus publickly held forth, that is to ſay, <hi>all ſuch</hi> perſons as are of our own Profeſſion, ſhall not be reſtrained from <hi>their</hi> profeſſion, but <hi>all</hi> ſuch Perſons ſhall have encouragement and equal protection in the profeſſion, &amp;c. and no others; ſo ſetting up one <hi>Profeſſion</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> onely, and protecting onely ſuch as are of that <hi>Profeſſion;</hi> and this whileſt <hi>ye</hi> are ſpeaking of the <hi>fundamentals</hi> of the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> and <hi>the endeavouring the Settlement of this Common-wealth, upon ſuch a foundation as may aſſert, eſtabliſh, and ſecure the liberties of the people in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence unto all, as men and Chriſtians; and of your full and fixed reſolution (through the aſſiſtance of God) effectually, even to the hazzard of your lives, to endeavour the recovery and ſecurity of the ſame; and of the ſignal Providences wherein the Lord hath owned the Parliament, and you their forces, both by Sea and Land, in aſſerting that righteous Cauſe, wherein the civil and religious liberties of the People of theſe Nations are involved, ſo as all open oppoſition was beaten down before them, and of the Diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which that publick Spirit, which appeared in that work, hath received ſince that time, in the late changes of Government:</hi> And <hi>of another raiſed up, drawing back to the ſame things the Parliament had contended againſt, even to the hazxard of the Eſſentials of that cauſe.</hi> And laſtly, <hi>of your thinking it your Duty, upon ſerious thoughts of heart, once more to appear</hi> againſt <hi>thoſe back-ſliding wayes.</hi> I ſay, whileſt <hi>ye</hi> are ſpeaking of ſuch things as theſe, in the <hi>Preamble</hi> to this <hi>your</hi> profeſſion; Are not <hi>your</hi> eyes yet open? Do <hi>ye</hi> not yet ſee how <hi>ye</hi> are deceived, and who hath deceived <hi>you?</hi> And how the <hi>ſmoak</hi> of the <hi>bottomleſs Pit</hi> hath ſmothered <hi>you,</hi> whileſt the <hi>coerſive,</hi> or <hi>impoſing</hi> Spirit hath ſlipt up between <hi>your Repreſentation</hi> and Deliverance?</p>
               <p>Fifthly, The <hi>fifth</hi> exception is, that whereas <hi>your</hi> Settlement ſaith, <hi>ſo as they abuſe not this Liberty, to the actual diſturbance of the Publick Peace, on their parts;</hi> (words honeſt and good,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119149:14"/> neither limiting the Lord, nor ſtinting his witneſs, nor compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling conſcience, nor medling with worſhips, things of Religion and conſcience, but with what is proper, to the Magiſtrate to take cognizance of, and to exclude protection, <hi>viz.</hi> Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance, actual diſturbance (or diſturbance made by overt act, or force, qualifying it to the Law, and ſpeaking plainly that men may certainly know what it makes a tranſgreſſion) of the Publick peace, and this on their parts too, not on, nor by occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of, or under the pretence of them; ſuch as ſhall ſo abuſe the Liberty afforded them, ſhall not be protected) I ſay, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>your</hi> Settlement thus ſaith, this article leaves <hi>this</hi> clauſe whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out, and adds another altogether <hi>ſtrange</hi> and <hi>forraign</hi> and <hi>deſtructive</hi> to the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> contended for in the <hi>Warrs,</hi> and contained in the <hi>Settlement,</hi> viz. <hi>The di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance of others</hi> (ſaith the Article) <hi>in their way of worſhips,</hi> neither ſaying <hi>what</hi> diſturbance, or explaining <hi>what</hi> ſhall be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, to be ſuch a diſturbance, as ſhall exclude protection; nor of <hi>what</hi> worſhips, (for there are many worſhips uſed in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and there is but one true worſhip) and the <hi>true</hi> worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, who worſhip God <hi>in Spirit and truth, whome the Father ſeeks to worſhip him, (and the hour is come wherein the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers worſhip the Father in Spirit and in truth</hi>) ſeek not to man for <hi>protection</hi>) nor qualifying it to the <hi>Actual</hi> diſturbance of the <hi>Publick</hi> Peace, and this on <hi>their</hi> parts; but only to the <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance</hi> of <hi>others in their way of worſhips,</hi> (general words like the <hi>bottemleſs</hi> Pit, out of which <hi>they</hi> come) ſo that, be the <hi>worſhips,</hi> what they will, or the <hi>worſhippers,</hi> or the <hi>way</hi> of <hi>their</hi> worſhips, how <hi>falſe, invented, vile, wicked, hypocritical</hi> ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; be the <hi>occaſion, cauſe</hi> or <hi>ground,</hi> witneſſing againſt them, never ſo <hi>righteous, juſt</hi> and <hi>ſubſtantial;</hi> be the command of the <hi>Lord,</hi> never ſo <hi>urgent</hi> to bear witneſs againſt them; If any ſuch <hi>witneſs-bearing</hi> be, whether in the time, or place, or out of it, whether in Writing, Speaking, or Printing, whether in looking, ſtanding ſtill, or ſitting, (for it ſayes not, where nor when, nor what, nor how, but <hi>diſturbance</hi> in the general Term or latitude) This (as <hi>it</hi> hath been, and the <hi>witneſſes of God</hi> have ſuffered for, as to <hi>all</hi> theſe things, from <hi>this adulterous generation,</hi> and the <hi>humble Petition</hi> and <hi>Advice</hi> hath a <hi>Law</hi> for moſt of <hi>it,</hi> even to <hi>impriſonment, working</hi> and <hi>whipping, if they
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119149:15"/> ſpeak but to a Prieſt, as he is going to, or coming from his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip;</hi> yea, at the <hi>diſcretion</hi> (or rather <hi>malice) of the Juſtices</hi> (for moſt of them were <hi>their</hi> enemies on a <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> account, &amp; laid it <hi>cruelly</hi> upon them, being given up by <hi>your</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral &amp; you, in the time of <hi>your Degeneration, as ſheep to the ſlaughter</hi>) is now deſired by <hi>you,</hi> yea, that they be continued under the ſame <hi>ſlavery</hi> and <hi>ſufferings</hi> for <hi>it,</hi> and becauſe of <hi>conſcience</hi> for <hi>ever,</hi> and this in the <hi>day</hi> of <hi>your</hi> bewailing of, and ſaying <hi>ye deſire to take ſhame to your ſelves, wherein ſoever ye have back-ſlidden.</hi> For in that ye ſay, <hi>that all Laws,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to the contrary may be declared null and void,</hi> thoſe which are according to <hi>it,</hi> are ſuch as muſt be underſtood to be by <hi>you</hi> deſired to ſtand, yea, as the <hi>foundation</hi> of the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> for ſo ye lay <hi>it</hi> in this <hi>your</hi> Addreſs.</p>
               <p>I ſay, this as it hath been, ſo it muſt be deemed a <hi>Deſturbance</hi> in the conſtruction of the <hi>Law</hi> aforeſaid, which <hi>ye</hi> have thus provided to ſtand, unto which there muſt be recourſe, ye ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving not aſſigned the particulars wherein; yea, ſuch a one, as cuts off <hi>Protection,</hi> ſo that the <hi>Lord (in whom is the breath of your noſtrils</hi>) may not ſpeak, may not teſtifie againſt <hi>Idolatry</hi> or <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolators, falſe</hi> worſhips or <hi>falſe</hi> worſhippers, <hi>Prieſts</hi> or <hi>People,</hi> for thoſe who ſhall ſpeak <hi>his</hi> word, and be <hi>his</hi> witneſſes againſt <hi>ſuch</hi> worſhips, or worſhippers, or <hi>wayes</hi> of worſhips, muſt have no <hi>Protection;</hi> this is <hi>your new Cauſe</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> this the fruit of <hi>your</hi> late <hi>Repreſentation and Contrition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, the <hi>ſixt</hi> Exception is, that <hi>ye</hi> ſay in the concluſion of <hi>this</hi> Article, <hi>viz. And that all Laws, Statutes, Ordinances and Clauſes, in any Laws, Statutes, and Ordinances, to the contrary, may be declared null and void.</hi> That is to ſay, <hi>All</hi> Laws, Statutes, and Ordinances, and Clauſes in <hi>any</hi> Laws, Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, and Ordinances, for <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi> For <hi>this</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, excluding <hi>all</hi> Profeſſions from <hi>Protection,</hi> but <hi>it</hi> ſelf, (as <hi>I</hi> have proved) cuts off <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> to <hi>any</hi> other <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> but <hi>it</hi> ſelf, and <hi>all</hi> Laws, &amp;c. to the contrary of <hi>this</hi> profeſſion, which ſo cut off, <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> being <hi>voided</hi> and <hi>made null,</hi> it <hi>makes null and void,</hi> whatſoever is in the <hi>Laws</hi> for <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi> Are <hi>ye</hi> awakened yet? Do <hi>ye</hi> yet ſee where <hi>ye</hi> are, and how <hi>ye</hi> have ſhut out, and barred the door a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seventhly, (to add no more) the <hi>ſeventh</hi> exception is, that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119149:15"/> 
                  <hi>ye</hi> do at all therein, meddle with <hi>Conſcience,</hi> as to the <hi>things</hi> of <hi>God, things Spiritual</hi> or <hi>Evangelical,</hi> which (as <hi>I</hi> have proved out of <hi>your</hi> own mouths) <hi>quite changes</hi> the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and layes the foundation of (what <hi>ye</hi> call) a <hi>free State</hi> or <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> in the <hi>thraldome</hi> of <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus much by way of exception to this <hi>ſixth</hi> Article of <hi>your</hi> Addreſs, upon comparing it with the <hi>third</hi> Article, under the ninth general Head of <hi>your</hi> Settlement concerning <hi>Religion;</hi> I ſhall now give you in <hi>your</hi> own words, what <hi>your</hi> ſelves have ſaid, of <hi>your</hi> ſaid Settlement, to the Nation in <hi>your</hi> Declaration thereunto annext, and ſo conclude this <hi>my ſecond</hi> inſtance, out of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> 
                  <hi>it</hi> is taken, to prove, &amp; by which <hi>I</hi> have fully proved, out of <hi>your</hi> own mouths, that this <hi>ſixt</hi> Article <hi>quite changeth the Cauſe, from what it was, to that which it was againſt. Your</hi> words in <hi>your ſaid</hi> Declaration to <hi>your</hi> ſaid Settlement, Pag. 28, 29. follow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We ſhall not otherwiſe commend it,</hi> (ſay ye of your Settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) <hi>than to ſay, it contains the beſt, and moſt hopeful foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the Peace, and future well government of this Nation, that we can deviſe, or think on, within the line of humane Power; and ſuch wherein all the people intereſted in the Land, (that have not particular intereſts of advantage and power over others, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided from that which is common and Publick, are indifferently and equally provided for. And we call the conſciences of all that read or hear it, to witneſs, whether we have therein provided, or propounded any thing of advantage to our ſelves, in any capacity above others; or ought, but what is as good for one as for another. And therefore, as we doubt not, but the Parliament being now freed from the obſtructing, and perverting Counſels of ſuch Members, by many of whom a corrupt complyance, with the Kings intereſt hath been driven on, and all Settlement otherwiſe hath hitherto hindred) thoſe remaining worthy Patriots; will, for the main allow thereof, and give their Seal of Approbation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. So we deſire, and hope, that all good people of England, whoſe heart God ſhall make ſenſible of their, and our common concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therein; and of the uſefulneſs, and ſuitableneſs thereof, to the Publick ends it holds forth, will cordially embrace it, and by ſubſcription declare their concurrence, and according thereto, when it ſhall be tendred to them, as is directed therein, wherein, if it ſhall pleaſe God, we ſhall find a good reception of it wiih the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119149:16"/> people of the Nation, or the well affected therein, we ſhall rejoyce at the hoped good to the Conmon-wealth, which thorow Gods mercy may redound therefrom, and that God hath vouchſafed thereby to make us inſtrumental for any good Settlement to this poor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed Country, as he hath formerly made us for the avoyding of evil. But if God ſhall (in his righteous Judgment towards this Land) ſuffer the people to be ſo blinded, as not to ſee this their own common good, and freedome, endeavoured to be provided for therein, or any be ſo deluded, (to their own and the Publick prejudice) as to make oppoſition thereto, whereby the effect of it be hindred, we have yet by the preparation, and tender of it, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged our conſciences to God, and duty to our native country, in our utmoſt endeavours for a Settlement, (to the beſt of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings,) unto a juſt Publick intereſt; and hope we ſhall be acquitted before God, and good men, from the blame of any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther troubles, diſtractions, or miſeries to the Kingdome, which may ariſe thorow the neglect, or rejection thereof, or oppoſition thereto.</hi> Words truly <hi>ſerious,</hi> and <hi>deep,</hi> than which, I need ſay no more in this matter for <hi>your</hi> convincement, and which will be a witneſs againſt <hi>you</hi> for ever, <hi>except ye repent,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having thus treated, of the <hi>matter</hi> of the <hi>ſaid ſixth</hi> Article of <hi>your</hi> Addreſs, <hi>I</hi> ſhall enquire a little concerning the <hi>language</hi> of it, whoſe <hi>language</hi> it is.</p>
               <p>The <hi>language</hi> of <hi>your</hi> ſolemn declarations, &amp;c. it is not, as hath been made manifeſt.</p>
               <p>The <hi>language</hi> of the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> it is not, as hath been abundantly proved.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Language</hi> of <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> it is not, for <hi>it</hi> reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <hi>it,</hi> and where <hi>Conſcience</hi> is reſtrained, it cannot be ſaid to be at Liberty.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Language</hi> of a <hi>Free-Sate,</hi> it is not, for where <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> thus ſuffers, the <hi>perſons</hi> or <hi>outward</hi> man is not <hi>free,</hi> and indeed it is the <hi>perſon,</hi> or <hi>outward</hi> man, that ſuffers in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtriction of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> for <hi>Conſcience</hi> cannot be touched by an <hi>outward</hi> Power, but the <hi>veſſel</hi> in which it is. And ſo the <hi>right</hi> of <hi>freedom</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> is a <hi>civil Right,</hi> and a <hi>civil Right</hi> it is to have the <hi>freedome</hi> of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> And where this <hi>Liberty</hi> is abridged by a <hi>State,</hi> that <hi>State</hi> is not <hi>free,</hi> For (according to the received <hi>Axiome</hi>) a <hi>free mind,</hi> and a <hi>free ſpeech,</hi> and a <hi>Free State,</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:119149:16"/> go together, and weere the <hi>two former</hi> are wanting, the <hi>later</hi> is not, nor doth it call ſuch a people <hi>happy.</hi> But on the contrary ſaith it, <hi>faelix cui libera gens, libera mens, libera lingua,</hi> (or) a <hi>happy</hi> people, where there is a <hi>free</hi> Nation (or <hi>State</hi>) a <hi>free mind</hi> (or Conſcience) a <hi>free</hi> ſpeech (or profeſſion) and where <hi>all</hi> profeſſions are excluded, but <hi>one,</hi> and Proviſion made onely for that <hi>one</hi> Profeſſion, how can there be ſaid to be a <hi>Weale Common,</hi> or a <hi>Common-Wealth?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Language</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> the <hi>faith of Gods Elect,</hi> it is not, for <hi>that</hi> never ſought to enforce <hi>it</hi> ſelf (as <hi>I</hi> have ſaid) otherwiſe then by commending it ſelf <hi>to that of God in every mans Conſcience.</hi> And the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Chief Prieſts</hi> and <hi>Rulers,</hi> who <hi>commanded them to ſpeak no more in that name</hi> (who ſpake in the <hi>Temple</hi> in <hi>that</hi> name, againſt the <hi>worſhips</hi> thereof, and for <hi>that</hi> cauſe were <hi>ſent</hi> to <hi>Priſon,</hi> and <hi>ſtockt</hi> and <hi>whipt) whether it be better to obey God or Man, judge ye.</hi> And the <hi>Lord</hi> ſaith, <hi>for as much as this people draw near me with their mouth, and with their lips do honour me, and their feare towards me, is taught by the precepts of men, therefore I will proceed to do a marvellous work among this people; even a marvellious work, and a wonder, the wiſdom of their wiſe men ſhall periſh, and the underſtanding of their prudent ſhall be hid; your</hi> Caſe at this Day.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Language</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> of <hi>Humanity,</hi> it is not; For, <hi>what man ever hated</hi> (caſt out of protection) <hi>his own fleſh?</hi> And <hi>they</hi> that were <hi>without natural affection,</hi> were ſuch as <hi>liked not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain God in their knowledge, therefore God gave them up to a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate mind.</hi> And <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience is a natural</hi> Right, (as ſaid your <hi>late General</hi> to the <hi>Parliament, September</hi> 12. 1654.) And ſo, to force <hi>Conſcience,</hi> is all one, as to force <hi>nature,</hi> that is to ſay, to <hi>murder:</hi> And the <hi>common Law</hi> voids all <hi>Statute</hi> Laws made againſt <hi>nature,</hi> and all the <hi>Judges</hi> cannot make that a <hi>Law,</hi> which is againſt <hi>Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Language</hi> of <hi>thoſe</hi> who would deſire <hi>Liberty</hi> for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (which was once <hi>your</hi> Caſe) of <hi>thoſe</hi> who <hi>do as they would be done to,</hi> it is not; for <hi>that</hi> which impoſes <hi>its</hi> own profeſſion, with excluſion of <hi>all</hi> others, would not be impoſed upon <hi>it</hi> ſelf. And if <hi>it</hi> be Lawful for a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> as a <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> or for <hi>one</hi> generationn of Men, becauſe in <hi>Power</hi> to meddle with <hi>Religion,</hi> to <hi>impoſe their profeſſion,</hi> it is lawful for <hi>another</hi> generation of men,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119149:17"/> as they come into <hi>Power,</hi> to impoſe their profeſſion. And ſo all the <hi>blood</hi> and <hi>ſufferings</hi> of the <hi>Martyrs</hi> and the <hi>witneſſes</hi> of <hi>God</hi> throughout <hi>all</hi> generations, againſt the <hi>impoſed</hi> profeſſion of the Men in <hi>power,</hi> in <hi>each</hi> generation, comes to be <hi>juſtified,</hi> and the <hi>generation</hi> of the <hi>Juſt,</hi> to be <hi>condemned.</hi> And the <hi>Queſtion,</hi> as to the <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> the <hi>right,</hi> is not, whether it be in <hi>truth,</hi> but whether there be <hi>power.</hi> Now <hi>no</hi> Profeſſion can be aſſured of <hi>its</hi> Station, where <hi>one</hi> is excluded; But muſt expect to vary ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the mutability of <hi>him</hi> or <hi>them,</hi> who have <hi>power</hi> to their <hi>will,</hi> as the dayes of <hi>Henry, 8. Edward, 6. Q. Mary,</hi> and <hi>Q. Elizabeth:</hi> in this <hi>Nation</hi> do abundantly witneſs.</p>
               <p>The Language of this Parliament it was not (they held another ballance) till they ſpake after you.</p>
               <p>To conclude; The <hi>Language</hi> of <hi>your late Repreſentation,</hi> April 6. 1659. Upon this ſence of <hi>your</hi> danger, it is not; for therein <hi>ye</hi> ſay, <hi>that ye have, as Members of the Army, often ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly declared, not without appeals to God, for your ſincerity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that ye did engage in Judgment and Conſcience, for the juſt Rights and Liberties, Civil and Religious,</hi> of <hi>your Countries, and not as a Mercenary Army, that ye had been ſilent ſo long, that ye feared, it had been a diſadvantage to the Cauſe, and bred (though ye hoped groundleſs) jealouſies of you, in many of your friends, and till ye and and all that is dear to you, the intreſt ye have ſo long contended for, was in danger to be loſt.</hi> That <hi>being then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſenſe of imminent dangers, and neceſſities awakned, ye did in a deep ſenſe of miſery and approaching judgment threatned, and purſuance of your duty in all humility repreſent, that the Good Old Cauſe againſt Tyranny and intollerable oppreſſion in matters Civil, and Religious, whereupon ye firſt ingaged, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which the Lord had, in ſuch a continued ſeries of Providence, given ſo ſignal a Teſtimony, and for the carrying on whereof there had been, ſuch a plentiful pouring forth of Treaſures, Prayers, Tears and Blood, during the late warr (in the difficulties and dangers whereof, ye alſo, the lively Monuments of Patience and mercy, had had your ſhares) was very frequently and publickly d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided and reproached, and the implacable adverſaries thereof, promiſed themſelves, to be ſo far in poſſeſſion, and Maſters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, that they began to appear, every where viſible among you, and to mix themſelves, in the midſt of thoſe places, where that cauſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119149:17"/> was wont to receive its chiefeſt countenance and ſhelter. So that upon the whole, ye did evidently ſee, there was but a ſtep betwixt the publick Cauſe of theſe nations, wherein ye had been ſo ſignally bleſt, and owned of God and good men, and the death thereof; and that it was not likely to expire without a ſure preſage of the ſad Funerals, of the dear and never enough valued peace of theſe your Native Countreys:</hi> That <hi>ye could not but bewail your own great failings, and turnings aſide, and that wherein ſoever ye had back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhidden, ye had cauſe, and deſired, to take ſhame to your ſelves. That ye were then as ever, equally endeared to your Good Old Cauſe, and utter enemies to all Tyranny, oppreſſion, and diſturbance of the publick Peace; under what pretences ſoever.</hi> And laſtly, <hi>ye</hi> deſire, that <hi>there may be ſuch a publick aſſerting of the Good Old Cauſe, and Juſtification of all proceedings, in proſecution and maintenance thereof, and Declaration againſt its enemies, as may for the future, deter all Perſons, from ſpeaking, or attempting any thing to the prejudice thereof, and of the Perſons that have acted in proſecution of it, and afford preſent ſecurity to the civil &amp; Riligious Rights and Liberties of theſe Nations, and the Peace thereof.</hi> And <hi>that the Liberty of good and well affected people, in repairing with freedome to their meetings for the worſhip of God (of late much violated by indicting, and impriſoning many of their Perſons) may be ſtill aſſerted and vindicated.</hi> But this <hi>ſixth</hi> Article of <hi>your</hi> Addreſs, cuts of <hi>Religious Right,</hi> viz. <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> (and conſequently <hi>civil,</hi> for as I have ſhewed) <hi>they</hi> cannot be ſeparated, but where a man ſuffers in the <hi>Liberty</hi> of his <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he</hi> ſuffers in <hi>his perſon</hi>) and <hi>caſts</hi> out of <hi>Protection,</hi> ſuch whoſe <hi>Conſciences,</hi> cannot be bounded by <hi>your</hi> ſaid Profeſſion (the <hi>people ye</hi> mind in this laſt clauſe, who muſt <hi>witneſs</hi> againſt <hi>falſe</hi> worſhippers and worſhips, and the <hi>wayes</hi> of them (the <hi>Lord</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving) even through <hi>death</hi> it ſelf, ſhould that be inflicted; As <hi>it</hi> hath caſt away the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> as ſoon as <hi>ye</hi> are delivered from the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Dangers</hi> and <hi>neceſſities,</hi> under the <hi>deep</hi> ſenſe of which the <hi>Honeſty</hi> in <hi>you,</hi> wrote in <hi>your</hi> ſaid Repreſentation, as hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſt. And ſo all that <hi>ye</hi> have ſaid, returns on <hi>your</hi> heads, and is <hi>your</hi> own judgment pronounced by <hi>your</hi> ſelves, and aggravates <hi>your</hi> condemnation.</p>
               <p>Whoſe <hi>Language</hi> is it them?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Friends, I</hi> ſhall tell <hi>you,</hi> and in the fear of <hi>God,</hi> ſeriouſly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119149:18"/> conſider it, It is the <hi>Language</hi> of that <hi>Spirit,</hi> which <hi>firſt</hi> divided from the <hi>Common Cauſe,</hi> to ſet up <hi>it</hi> ſelf over <hi>it,</hi> (as <hi>I</hi> have ſhewed in the <hi>State</hi> of the <hi>Caſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> caſt <hi>ſuch</hi> from whom <hi>it</hi> divided, and over whom <hi>it</hi> ſought to ſet up <hi>it</hi> ſelf) out of <hi>all</hi> places of <hi>Truſt, Military,</hi> and <hi>Civil,</hi> and perſecuted as <hi>ſchiſmatical Hereticks.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> obſtructed the paſſing of the <hi>Liſt</hi> of <hi>Officers,</hi> for the <hi>New Model</hi> of the <hi>Army,</hi> (in which were ſome of <hi>you</hi>) ſo long, that the <hi>members</hi> of <hi>this</hi> Parliament, (then called the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons</hi>) were forced by reaſon of the danger thereby, threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the overthrow of the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> to let the members of the <hi>other</hi> Houſe (then called the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Peers</hi>) know, that if <hi>they</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curred not, <hi>they</hi> would paſs <hi>it</hi> without them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> made all the obſtructions to you in the <hi>New Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> divided <hi>ye</hi> at <hi>Blandford</hi> in <hi>Dorſetſhire,</hi> upon <hi>your</hi> firſt march, and ſent part of <hi>you</hi> to relieve <hi>Taunton</hi> in the <hi>Weſt,</hi> (where <hi>ye</hi> might have been eaten up like as <hi>ye</hi> were preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged) and part of <hi>ye</hi> againſt <hi>Oxford,</hi> (where <hi>ye</hi> might have been beaten off) and part of <hi>ye,</hi> to joyn with the <hi>Scots</hi> Army, as the <hi>field</hi> Army, (where <hi>ye</hi> might have been interpoſed, (the Scots retreating towards <hi>Weſt-moorland</hi>) and part of <hi>ye</hi> to the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Ely</hi> in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> (where <hi>ye</hi> might have been ſurprized) which put a <hi>lock</hi> at <hi>South-ham</hi> in <hi>Warwick-ſhire,</hi> upon the <hi>feet</hi> of that <hi>part</hi> of <hi>you,</hi> as followed the <hi>Kings</hi> Army, who were marching into the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> aſſotiation, (your <hi>untoucht</hi> Magazine for <hi>men</hi> and <hi>money</hi>) to preſerve that, commanding <hi>ye</hi> not to <hi>fight</hi> them, but to <hi>march</hi> to <hi>Oxford,</hi> to <hi>beleaguer Garriſons, ere ye were Maſters of the Field,</hi> or ſo much as <hi>recruted,</hi> as was <hi>promiſed,</hi> leaving the <hi>enemy</hi> to <hi>his</hi> pleaſure. And all <hi>this</hi> near about the ſame time, that <hi>ye</hi> might have been cut off, whatever had been the iſſue of <hi>it</hi> to the Nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> ſought to enſnare <hi>ye</hi> into a <hi>Scotch</hi> Presbytery, and <hi>intereſt,</hi> or to divide <hi>you</hi> among <hi>your</hi> ſelves, by reaſon thereof, in ſending order for the covenant to be taken, by <hi>all</hi> of <hi>you,</hi> which <hi>many</hi> could not, in <hi>tenderneſs</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and ſo <hi>ye</hi> laid <hi>it</hi> aſide.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> was offended at <hi>your</hi> not receiving <hi>its</hi> Miniſters as your
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119149:18"/> 
                  <hi>Chaplains,</hi> at <hi>your</hi> ſpeaking, or preaching to <hi>your</hi> Souldiers; At <hi>your</hi> going into <hi>Steeple-houſes,</hi> and <hi>ſpeaking</hi> there, and ſent <hi>orders</hi> from the (then) <hi>Houſe</hi> of Peers, to reſtrain <hi>it,</hi> which <hi>ye</hi> obſerved not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> when the over-ruling hand of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and inevitable neceſſity, had brought the greateſt part of <hi>you</hi> together at <hi>Naſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> after ſuch <hi>your</hi> diviſion, longed and looked for, and was over confident, in <hi>its</hi> hopes of <hi>your</hi> deſtruction, ſcoffing <hi>ye</hi> with the <hi>deriſion</hi> of the <hi>New Nodel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> was ſore pained at the heart, and grieved at that <hi>victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>your</hi> ſucceſſes, though <hi>it</hi> was the <hi>Nations</hi> reviving, and covered over the <hi>Sorrows</hi> of <hi>War,</hi> with the <hi>garment</hi> of <hi>rejoycing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> (thoſe <hi>Wars</hi> being ended) endeavoured to enforce <hi>its</hi> reduced <hi>General Eſſex,</hi> by the <hi>Scotch</hi> Army, <hi>your</hi> Commander in <hi>Chief,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> Officers in <hi>your</hi> ſteads, as a <hi>check</hi> upon <hi>your</hi> victories, and thought <hi>it</hi> too much for <hi>you,</hi> to breath in <hi>Engliſh</hi> aire, by whom (as inſtruments) <hi>England</hi> breathed, but by <hi>his</hi> ſudden death was prevented.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> remanded <hi>General Liſle</hi> from <hi>Ireland,</hi> as ſoon almoſt, as <hi>he</hi> had put <hi>his</hi> foot thereon, after the <hi>great</hi> expence of that expedition, and delivered <hi>all</hi> into <hi>Inchequin's</hi> hand (who ſoon gave <hi>it</hi> to the King) to ſerve as a <hi>ballance</hi> on <hi>you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> emptyed ſome <hi>Garriſons</hi> of <hi>you</hi> and <hi>your</hi> friends, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantled <hi>others,</hi> ſeized the <hi>Armies Artillery,</hi> and <hi>Ammunition</hi> in <hi>its</hi> hands, that it might be <hi>Treaſon</hi> in any elſe to touch <hi>it,</hi> in preparation againſt <hi>ye,</hi> and <hi>hanged</hi> many for what <hi>they</hi> had done as <hi>Souldiers</hi> for the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> would have divided and deſtroyed you, upon the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the <hi>Reliefe</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and judged <hi>ye Traytors</hi> by its majority in Parliament, upon the <hi>report</hi> of a <hi>harmleſs</hi> petition intended by <hi>you,</hi> to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> by <hi>your Generals</hi> hand, for <hi>your</hi> rights as <hi>Souldiers,</hi> unſeen and unheard, and enforced <hi>you</hi> to <hi>embody</hi> and <hi>engage to and with one another, at Triplo Heath, for your mutual preſervation, and not to diſband or divide, nor ſuffer your ſelves to be divided, or diſbanded, till the common ends, on which ye, and your friends engaged, and your grievances, were ſecured and ſatisfyed.</hi> Though <hi>they</hi> intended no ſuch thing as the <hi>reliefe</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> by <hi>you,</hi> but by <hi>this</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> (as <hi>I</hi> ſaid)
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119149:19"/> to deſtroy <hi>you;</hi> for <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>Eleven</hi> Members confeſt, viz. <hi>That their Miniſters put them on this attempt againſt you, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring it no leſs than damnation, to ſend ſuch Schiſmaticks as you, into Ireland:</hi> So far were <hi>they</hi> from intending <hi>you</hi> thither, &amp; the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments</hi> for <hi>Ireland</hi> were kept near a <hi>year</hi> (ſome of <hi>them</hi>) quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering on the Countrey, in reſerve for, and ordered to be drawn up for <hi>this</hi> end, viz. to Ballance <hi>your</hi> forces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> prepared <hi>Shibboleths</hi> for <hi>your Conſciences,</hi> whileſt <hi>your</hi> Bodies were drawn in the <hi>field,</hi> for the <hi>Liberties</hi> of <hi>your</hi> Countrey, as witneſs the <hi>Ordinance</hi> for <hi>Blaſphemy</hi> (commonly called the <hi>Bloudy Ordinance,</hi> brought in by <hi>Bacon</hi> and <hi>Tate</hi>) to torture <hi>your</hi> bodies for <hi>your Conſciences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> ſtirred up the <hi>Rabble</hi> of Boyes, into that <hi>inſufferable</hi> and <hi>unheard</hi> affront on the <hi>Parliament</hi> (the <hi>firſt</hi> that ever was, on ſuch an Aſſembly) whom ſome of <hi>Its</hi> Rabbi Prieſts were ſeen to clap on the Shouldiers to encourage them thereunto) forcing the <hi>Speaker,</hi> and ſuch of the <hi>Members,</hi> in whom that <hi>Spirit</hi> ruled not, to fly to <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>raiſing</hi> up; and <hi>Garriſoning</hi> the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and arming the <hi>deſperate</hi> Reformadoes againſt <hi>ye;</hi> and endeavouring to draw the whole <hi>Nation</hi> alſo, and <hi>Scotland</hi> (ſome of whoſe <hi>forces</hi> were <hi>near</hi> the borders on <hi>their</hi> march) ſo endeavouring to engage this <hi>poor haraſſed</hi> Countrey into <hi>blood</hi> again, to ſatiate its revenge, becauſe by <hi>you, Peace</hi> was brought, and flowed in unto <hi>their</hi> Countrey.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> trinkled with the <hi>King,</hi> at the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Wight,</hi> and made a <hi>private</hi> bargain with <hi>him,</hi> and ſtirred up the <hi>People</hi> in the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> to petition for a <hi>Perſonal Treaty,</hi> and under <hi>that</hi> and the pretence of <hi>his</hi> impriſonment, to raiſe Armes again, which was boforehand Plotted, and formed by <hi>inſurrections,</hi> and <hi>tumults,</hi> &amp; put <hi>ye</hi> to fight it over again more ſharply than before, 2000 to 10000, from <hi>Pembroke Caſtle,</hi> to <hi>Preſton</hi> in <hi>LANCASIRE</hi> throughout, and a thwart the <hi>Nation,</hi> yea to march to Eden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough, and brought in <hi>Duke Hamilton</hi> and <hi>his</hi> Army, which <hi>it</hi> would not vote (viz. the then <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Peers</hi>) an <hi>Invaſion,</hi> and out of queſtion, had queſtioned <hi>ye</hi> for it, had <hi>ye</hi> not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed againſt him, which ſigned the <hi>Treaſonable</hi> Engagement in <hi>London,</hi> and Petitioned for <hi>Batten</hi> to be <hi>Vice Admiral,</hi> (who had received his <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from the <hi>Prince</hi>) and broke the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,</hi> and would not Settle the <hi>Militia;</hi> And voted the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:119149:19"/> of the <hi>King</hi> at the <hi>Treaty</hi> at the <hi>Iſle</hi> of <hi>Wight,</hi> in order to a <hi>ſafe</hi> Peace, and held <hi>ye</hi> out at <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> and got ſo into the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> and put <hi>ye</hi> ſo to it there, that <hi>ye</hi> were neceſſitated for the preſervation of the Publick intereſt, (<hi>ye</hi> had contended for) and <hi>your</hi> ſelves and friends, to purge the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons,</hi> of <hi>thoſe</hi> who had <hi>ſo</hi> voted, and who carryed on, and were for a <hi>corrupt</hi> cloſure, and complyance with the <hi>King,</hi> yea, to try the <hi>King,</hi> to lay aſide the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Peers;</hi> to exheriditate <hi>his</hi> iſſue, to extirpate <hi>Monarchy,</hi> to chang the <hi>Government</hi> into a <hi>Free-ſtate</hi> or <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> without a <hi>King,</hi> or <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Peers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> put <hi>ye</hi> to a ſudden expedition in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to recover that which was (in a manner) loſt to the <hi>Gates</hi> of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and when with <hi>wonderful</hi> ſucceſs, and <hi>hard</hi> ſervice, <hi>ye</hi> had reduced <hi>that</hi> Nation, would not thank <hi>God</hi> for the <hi>deliverance,</hi> as <hi>it</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to <hi>pray</hi> for <hi>your</hi> ſucceſs. But the more <hi>ye</hi> were loaden with <hi>victories</hi> for the <hi>Nations</hi> ſake, the more was <hi>it burthened</hi> with <hi>grief</hi> for the <hi>ſake</hi> of <hi>your</hi> victories.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which</hi> became the <hi>third</hi> partie, to bring the <hi>Kings</hi> eldeſt Son and the <hi>Scotch</hi> together againſt the <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> with whom <hi>they</hi> joyned and Plotted, and whom <hi>it</hi> aſſiſted in <hi>Pulpit</hi> and <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe,</hi> and <hi>Commiſſioned Commiſſioners</hi> to joyn with the <hi>Scots</hi> in <hi>Treaty</hi> with him at <hi>Breda,</hi> (whom <hi>they</hi> had declared <hi>King</hi>) and joyned in the concluſion of the <hi>Treaty,</hi> viz. <hi>to put him by force of Armes, in the throne of England;</hi> and wrought off, <hi>your Renowned General Fairfax,</hi> from leading <hi>you</hi> againſt them, and to lay down <hi>his</hi> Commiſſion, upon ſome <hi>ſcruples</hi> that were in <hi>him, it</hi> thinking thereby to have broken <hi>ye</hi> (in all which <hi>its</hi> Prieſts were chiefly active and conſulted) and put <hi>ye</hi> to <hi>it</hi> early to look to <hi>your</hi> own Houſe, by marching into <hi>theirs,</hi> who were preparing for <hi>yours,</hi> and to paſs thorow the <hi>ſore</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities of <hi>wet</hi> and <hi>weather,</hi> of <hi>want</hi> of <hi>victuals</hi> and <hi>proviſion,</hi> in a <hi>cold naked</hi> and <hi>Sterile</hi> Countrey, during the <hi>winter</hi> ſeaſon, and to attend under <hi>theſe</hi> upon the <hi>Scots</hi> couched in their Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, whileſt the <hi>Plots</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> might have ſet <hi>England</hi> in a flame behind <hi>ye</hi> (on which <hi>they</hi> waited) and miſerable ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, ſhould, in a manner reduce <hi>your</hi> Souldiers, in the midſt of <hi>ye,</hi> into little better condition, than of <hi>dying</hi> men (which was even effected) that then <hi>its</hi> Army, before <hi>ye,</hi> might ſwallow ye up (which <hi>it</hi> attempted) even when all <hi>thoſe</hi> diſtreſſes had even
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119149:20"/> compaſſed <hi>ye</hi> about, and it ſo thought <hi>it,</hi> and <hi>it</hi> was ſo, and then it vaunted <hi>it</hi> ſelf, and ſpake <hi>proudly,</hi> and ſought to come between the paſſages and <hi>ye,</hi> that <hi>ye</hi> might not get home into <hi>your</hi> Countrey; And then ſought <hi>ye</hi> at <hi>Dunbar,</hi> where <hi>ye</hi> were delivered with a <hi>wonderful</hi> Deliverance. My <hi>Friends,</hi> let <hi>it</hi> never be forgotten, nor the <hi>wonderful</hi> Diſcovery, and breaking of <hi>their</hi> Plots in <hi>England,</hi> which immediately foreran <hi>it,</hi> and correſponded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and were on the Point of execution to have ſerved <hi>it, (Call to mind the former things, and let the things that are paſt come into Remembrance.</hi>) And then held <hi>yee</hi> there another winter, whileſt <hi>Plots,</hi> and <hi>deſigns</hi> were forming up in <hi>England</hi> again, by <hi>Chriſtopher Love</hi> and his <hi>Brethren,</hi> the <hi>Preiſts</hi> and <hi>Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates,</hi> and the <hi>Cavaleire</hi> Party (who thought to have attacht thoſe of <hi>you</hi> in <hi>this</hi> Nation, in the <hi>depth</hi> of <hi>Winter,</hi> by a <hi>general</hi> Inſurrection, which the breaking forth of that of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk</hi> hindred, before the <hi>general</hi> Day was come) and when <hi>they</hi> were diſappointed thereby, wrought <hi>yet</hi> more ſubtilly, and made all things ready againſt <hi>Spring</hi> to have riſen up generally as <hi>one</hi> man (<hi>Cavaleir</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi>) to have ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, <hi>M. G. Maſſies</hi> deſigned invaſion of <hi>England,</hi> with a <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gade</hi> of <hi>Horſe,</hi> which being alſo diſcovered and broken, put <hi>yee</hi> upon <hi>your</hi> attempts on <hi>Fife,</hi> wherein <hi>ye</hi> being made ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful as formerly, <hi>it</hi> ſlipt into England (as <hi>its</hi> laſt Refuge) whileſt <hi>ye</hi> were engaged at St. <hi>Johnſtons,</hi> &amp; lay down in <hi>Worceſter,</hi> till <hi>your</hi> long march from <hi>Johnſtons</hi> reached <hi>them,</hi> and <hi>ye</hi> with your friends in <hi>this</hi> Nation joyning together, ſoon encompaſſed <hi>them</hi> about, and gave them, and it, a <hi>total</hi> overthrow.</p>
               <p>To conclude, <hi>which</hi> was glad at the <hi>late</hi> Interruption of the <hi>preſent</hi> Parliament; and complyed with <hi>him</hi> that made <hi>it,</hi> and ſet <hi>him</hi> up, that it might ſet <hi>it</hi> ſelf up, by <hi>him</hi> again, in a <hi>ſingle Perſon,</hi> and <hi>Houſe of Lords,</hi> and in <hi>all</hi> things that <hi>it</hi> had before endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, upon <hi>Conſcience</hi> and the <hi>Liberties</hi> of the <hi>Nation;</hi> And <hi>which</hi> by <hi>him</hi> did ſet <hi>it</hi> ſelf up (in the late <hi>Humble Petition and Adviſe,</hi> and other <hi>Acts</hi> of that <hi>Parliament,</hi> over the <hi>Liberties</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> (wherein <hi>ye</hi> may read the <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage</hi> of <hi>this</hi> Article) and then (<hi>he</hi> being cut down, <hi>when he had built again the things that he deſtroyed, ſo making himſelf a Tranſgreſſor</hi>) ſought to over-run, and cut down <hi>you,</hi> who yet ſtood in <hi>its</hi> way, Trampling on the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> viz. <hi>in aſſerting a coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119149:20"/> power in them, in matters of Religion,</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> in <hi>its</hi> intended Declaration for a <hi>faſt</hi> (as this Article doth in <hi>you,</hi> where <hi>ye</hi> may read <hi>its Language</hi> again, even the <hi>Language</hi> of <hi>both</hi> to be the <hi>ſame,</hi> and from <hi>one</hi> Spirit) I ſay, trampling on the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>you,</hi> and the <hi>ſufferings</hi> of <hi>truth</hi> together (ſhewing what <hi>it</hi> would do as <hi>it</hi> had power, and who they were it looked upon as <hi>its</hi> enemies, viz. <hi>the Truth,</hi> the <hi>Cauſe</hi> and <hi>you Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> were a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>licted together) and prepared a <hi>Pit</hi> for <hi>you all,</hi> which opening <hi>its</hi> mouth wide, to ſwallow <hi>you</hi> up, and <hi>your</hi> eyes being opened to ſee it, ſtarted <hi>ye</hi> ſo that <hi>ye cryed</hi> to the <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed,</hi> and <hi>vowed</hi> (as in <hi>your</hi> late Repreſentation) who heard <hi>your</hi> Cry, and delivered <hi>you.</hi> Now being delivered, <hi>this</hi> Spirit ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected no other, than to be tumbled into the <hi>Pit,</hi> which <hi>it</hi> had digged for <hi>you,</hi> which was ready to receive <hi>it,</hi> and to cloſe <hi>its</hi> mouth upon <hi>it,</hi> unleſs <hi>it</hi> could ſo work as to enter into <hi>you</hi> (a <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult,</hi> and one would think, an <hi>impoſſible</hi> thing, as things ſtood) and in and by <hi>you,</hi> preſerve <hi>it</hi> ſelf out of <hi>it,</hi> and ſo ſet up <hi>it</hi> ſelf at laſt through <hi>you,</hi> over all, which by wrapping <hi>it</hi> ſelf in a <hi>friends</hi> mantle, and coming under <hi>it</hi> (viz. the <hi>Garment</hi> of a <hi>Prieſt</hi> who had formerly been <hi>your</hi> friend (<hi>ye</hi> may gueſs whom <hi>I</hi> mean) it hath (now) done; raiſing up <hi>it</hi> ſelf in <hi>you</hi> to do that, which a man looking upon you, as in <hi>your</hi> former Declarations and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngagements, and <hi>your</hi> late Repreſentation, and hour, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, and the ſenſe o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> them <hi>all</hi> that was upon <hi>you</hi>) would have thought impoſſible that ever <hi>ye</hi> ſhould do, and which will lead you further, (as <hi>ye</hi> are led by <hi>it</hi>) to do that which if a man ſhould tell <hi>you</hi> now, <hi>ye</hi> would ſay, <hi>are we Dogs thus to do?</hi> perking <hi>its</hi> head on, and over <hi>your</hi> ſhouldiers, above the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> (who had trod <hi>that</hi> Spirit under foot (and was now ready to make of <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> an utter end) and treading under foot the <hi>Good Old Cauſe,</hi> which on and over <hi>your</hi> ſhouldiers, and you upon <hi>it,</hi> had ſtood above <hi>it,</hi> and which by <hi>you</hi> had trod <hi>it</hi> under. This is a <hi>Lamentation,</hi> and ſhall be for a <hi>Lamentation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet, which of <hi>you</hi> of this is ſenſible, but ſo it is, after all <hi>your victories</hi> and <hi>apportunities,</hi> and <hi>deliverances</hi> over and upon, and from <hi>this</hi> Spirit and <hi>its</hi> workings, and <hi>this</hi> laſt eſpecially, which was the <hi>greateſt</hi> of all, by which <hi>this</hi> Spirit was given into your hand, as <hi>appointed by God to utter deſtruction,</hi> which would have deſtroyed <hi>ye) ye</hi> have let go out of <hi>your</hi> hand, the <hi>Spirit</hi> which
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119149:21"/> 
                  <hi>God hath appointed to utter deſtruction;</hi> Therefore <hi>your life,</hi> (or the <hi>life</hi> of <hi>thoſe</hi> of <hi>ye,</hi> or <hi>him,</hi> who wrought, and hath done <hi>it) ſhall go for its life,</hi> and <hi>your,</hi> or <hi>his people for its:</hi> Its faithfulneſs in <hi>me,</hi> to tell <hi>ye</hi> or <hi>him</hi> ſo, (and wo to <hi>me</hi> if <hi>I</hi> ſhould not being required of the <hi>Lord,</hi> of whom <hi>I</hi> have received <hi>it</hi>) However <hi>the King of Iſrael</hi> may take <hi>it,</hi> and <hi>go to his houſe heavy and diſpleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> ye know the <hi>hiſtory, Read</hi> and apply <hi>it</hi> to <hi>your</hi> ſelves in the caſe, <hi>ye</hi> who are concerned, who have done this thing, for it is <hi>your</hi> Portion, and ſhall <hi>aſſuredly</hi> come upon <hi>you</hi> from the <hi>Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, is not the <hi>day</hi> from the <hi>Lord,</hi> come upon <hi>you</hi> already? is not <hi>your ſtrength, your life,</hi> already gone? Are not <hi>your Locks</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready cut off? viz. <hi>your</hi> diſtinct Conſiſtency in <hi>your</hi> ſelves, to chuſe <hi>your</hi> General from among <hi>your</hi> ſelves, to receive <hi>your</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions and Orders, from ſuch <hi>your</hi> General, not to <hi>disband,</hi> or <hi>divide, nor to ſuffer your ſelves to be disbanded, or divided, till you, and the juſt grievance of you and your friends in the Nation, and the Cauſe, were fully ſatisfied,</hi> and <hi>ſecured,</hi> into which Engagement <hi>ye</hi> were neceſſicated at <hi>Triploe</hi> Heath, &amp; reſolved for the <hi>mutual</hi> preſervation, of <hi>your ſelves,</hi> and the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and <hi>your</hi> friends which were engaged in <hi>it,</hi> againſt this <hi>over-ruling</hi> Party in <hi>Parliament,</hi> who roſe up againſt <hi>it,</hi> and <hi>them,</hi> and <hi>you,</hi> and ordered <hi>your</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding for <hi>that</hi> purpoſe, that, <hi>ye</hi> and <hi>it,</hi> and <hi>them,</hi> might have been brought under at <hi>their</hi> pleaſure. So <hi>ye</hi> were no longer as an <hi>Army</hi> Commiſſionated by <hi>them,</hi> but as a <hi>Body</hi> of <hi>people;</hi> who upon <hi>inevitable</hi> neceſſity and <hi>manifeſt</hi> juſtice, where <hi>incorporated in,</hi> and <hi>with,</hi> and <hi>among your ſelves,</hi> and <hi>to</hi> and <hi>with your friends</hi> in the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> for the <hi>through</hi> Proſecution of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Liberty,</hi> in which <hi>ye</hi> were at <hi>firſt</hi> engaged, called out, entruſted and aſſiſted, againſt <hi>all</hi> attempts to the contrary what, and in whomſoever, which was of <hi>God.</hi> By vertue of which <hi>ye</hi> were in a capacity, and did eaſe <hi>this</hi> preſent Parliament of thoſe of <hi>their</hi> members, who carried on a <hi>corrupt</hi> and <hi>unſafe</hi> cloſure with the <hi>King,</hi> and with their <hi>obſtructing Counſels,</hi> (as <hi>ye</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare) <hi>not onely hindred the Settlement of the Common-wealth, but often endangered it;</hi> after that, the <hi>Speaker</hi> and <hi>thoſe</hi> Members of the Parliament (who were faithful to the <hi>Cauſe</hi>) being forced by the <hi>tumultuous</hi> violence of <hi>Boyes</hi> &amp; <hi>Reformadoes,</hi> to withdraw to <hi>you,</hi> were by <hi>you</hi> (notwithſtanding the <hi>raiſing</hi> of <hi>London</hi> in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119149:21"/> 
                  <hi>Armes,</hi> and endeavouring to do <hi>it</hi> through the <hi>Nation,</hi> and <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by the <hi>remaining Party</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi>) put into their <hi>Houſe</hi> again, and ſecured in their <hi>Seſſions;</hi> and laſtly, brought <hi>this</hi> Parliament to ſit again, after <hi>ſix</hi> years interruption, to the haz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarding of <hi>all,</hi> in which capacity <hi>ye</hi> ſhould ſtill have ſtood, and have been, as heretofore, the <hi>Honourable</hi> and <hi>happy</hi> Inſtruments of <hi>your</hi> Countries Liberties, and <hi>its life reſerve</hi> againſt <hi>all Tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> and <hi>intolerable oppreſſions,</hi> in <hi>matters Civil,</hi> and <hi>Religious,</hi> had <hi>ye</hi> remained with <hi>God;</hi> but it is (now) otherwiſe, <hi>ye</hi> are bowed down, <hi>ye</hi> are humbled, (as the caſe now ſtands) <hi>your</hi> laſt is done, <hi>your</hi> Locks are off; <hi>ye</hi> are bound, and <hi>ye</hi> have have bound <hi>your</hi> ſelves; <hi>ye</hi> can work (as now) no more <hi>ſuch deliverance in the Earth,</hi> for <hi>your</hi> ſelves or <hi>Countrey,</hi> as have been through <hi>your</hi> hands, <hi>it</hi> muſt <hi>come now from another place, ye</hi> are ſubmitted; and ye have ſubmitted <hi>your</hi> ſelves; <hi>ye</hi> are lower'd, and have brought <hi>your</hi> ſelves low (as now) and your <hi>Friends,</hi> and the <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> even to the <hi>ground,</hi> to the <hi>duſt. Your Maſters</hi> (as <hi>they</hi> come) may (now) <hi>put you to grind,</hi> at <hi>their</hi> pleaſures, to <hi>disband,</hi> to <hi>do</hi> as <hi>they</hi> will; and if <hi>ye</hi> ſhall hereafter go out, and <hi>ſhake your ſelves,</hi> when <hi>affliction is on you,</hi> as hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>ye</hi> will find <hi>your Cauſe</hi> (which whenſoever <hi>ye</hi> brought it in your <hi>hand,</hi> and could ſay in <hi>Truth, Lord here's the Cauſe, he</hi> never failed to deliver <hi>you,</hi> what ever were <hi>your</hi> ſtraits and <hi>Difficulties; I</hi> ſay, <hi>ye</hi> will find your Cauſe, <hi>your</hi> Locks, <hi>your</hi> ſtrength, <hi>your</hi> power, to be gone, and <hi>your</hi> ſelves bound as with <hi>Fetters of Braſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O! what will <hi>ye</hi> do then? and wither will <hi>ye</hi> go, when <hi>ye</hi> ſhall find <hi>it</hi> ſo, and <hi>both your eyes out,</hi> and <hi>night</hi> over <hi>you,</hi> and the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> removed from <hi>you,</hi> and that <hi>he</hi> anſwers <hi>ye</hi> not, <hi>neither by Dreames, nor by <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rim, nor by Prophet?</hi> If <hi>ye</hi> go to the <hi>Wizards,</hi> to <hi>thoſe</hi> who have <hi>familiar Spirits,</hi> to the <hi>falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> that <hi>ye</hi> have <hi>cut</hi> off throughout <hi>all</hi> theſe Nations, and deſire that <hi>it</hi> Divine unto <hi>you,</hi> and bring <hi>ye</hi> up <hi>him,</hi> whom <hi>ye</hi> ſhall name) who formerly was with <hi>you, (Samuel, the Prophet of the Lord, the Angel of his preſence,</hi> which went before <hi>you,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed <hi>ye,</hi> and delivered <hi>ye</hi> out of <hi>your ſtraits,</hi> and ſubdued <hi>all</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>you,</hi>) and the <hi>Witch</hi> to whom ye go, the <hi>Spirit</hi> which <hi>ye</hi> had cut off, and to which <hi>ye</hi> have promiſed, that <hi>no puniſhment ſhall
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119149:22"/> happen to it, for what it ſhall do, that it ſhall be protected,</hi> ſhall bring up to <hi>you, him</hi> whom <hi>ye</hi> name, viz. <hi>an old man covered with a mantle</hi> (the <hi>likeneſs</hi> of <hi>Samuel</hi>) and <hi>ye</hi> ſtoop with <hi>your</hi> face to the ground, and bow <hi>your</hi> ſelves, and upon <hi>his</hi> ſaying, <hi>why have ye diſquieted me, to bring me up?</hi> ye ſay to <hi>him, we are ſore diſtreſſed, and the Phyliſtians make Warr againſt us, and God is departed from us, and anſwereth us no more, neither by Prophets nor by dreams, and therefore we have called thee, that thou mayeſt make known unto us, what we ſhall do; he</hi> will anſwer <hi>you, wherefore then do ye ask of me, ſeeing the Lord is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from you, and is become your enemy; and the Lord hath done to you, as he had ſpoken by me: for the Lord hath rent the Kingdome out of your hand, and given it to your neighbour, even to David, becauſe ye obeyed not the voyce of the Lord, nor executed his fierce wrath upon Amalek. Therefore hath the Lord done this thing unto you this day; Moreover the Lord will alſo deliver Iſrael with ye, into the hands of the Phyliſtians, and to morrow ſhall ye and your Sons be with me; The Lord ſhall alſo deliver the Hoſt of Iſrael into the hands of the Phyliſtians,</hi> then will <hi>ye fall all along on the Earth, and be ſore afraid, and no ſtrength will be in you.</hi> And then will <hi>ye</hi> remember, that of <hi>theſe</hi> things <hi>ye</hi> were told, and warned in the <hi>day</hi> of <hi>your</hi> delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
               <p>And is it not juſt <hi>it</hi> ſhould be ſo? even that <hi>you</hi> who have ſo ſoon <hi>changed</hi> the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and thereby given up <hi>your</hi> power to the <hi>enemy,</hi> ſhould as ſoon have the caſe changed with <hi>you,</hi> viz. that <hi>your</hi> power ſhould be taken away, by <hi>your</hi> friends; that <hi>ye</hi> who have given up the <hi>Cauſe of Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther betrayed <hi>it,</hi> or rather are betray'd into <hi>it,</hi> ſhould be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven up to an incapacity <hi>any</hi> more to <hi>relieve,</hi> to <hi>ſecure it.</hi> So that <hi>deliverance,</hi> if <hi>it</hi> ariſe to <hi>conſoience</hi> (and ariſe <hi>it will when the great Hour is over, which is at hand, the like was never, nor ſhall be after it, in which the Lord alone will appear</hi>) muſt ariſe from ſome <hi>other</hi> place, <hi>ye</hi> have bound <hi>your</hi> ſelves, and are bound; and ſo how can <hi>it ariſe</hi> any more from <hi>you,</hi> this is that, indeed, which the Enemy endeavoured <hi>thorowout</hi> the warrs, and the <hi>Iate</hi> alterations ſince the warrs, that <hi>it</hi> might have <hi>its</hi> end upon <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>you,</hi> but could do never, becauſe ye <hi>held the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119149:22"/> Cauſe,</hi> now the <hi>thing</hi> hath proſpered againſt you, becauſe <hi>ye</hi> have <hi>not held the Cauſe,</hi> but changed <hi>it,</hi> to <hi>that</hi> of the <hi>Enemies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo, is not the <hi>Word</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> which <hi>I</hi> wrote unto <hi>you,</hi> from his mouth, and called to the <hi>Heavens,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>hear O Heavens,</hi> and to the <hi>Earth,</hi> ſaying, <hi>give ear O Earth, and be ye witneſſes, and all good men,</hi> (viz. If <hi>ye</hi> do not <hi>ſo,</hi> and <hi>ſo,</hi> as in <hi>your</hi> repreſentation ye have ſaid, and as in that <hi>my</hi> letter, is of it rehearſt and expreſt, which <hi>ye</hi> have not done, but the contrary) <hi>ye ſhall not proſper, the Lord hath ſpoken it. If ye ſtart aſide once more, farewel, ye have confeſt againſt your ſelves, and your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation is witneſs againſt you. Deliverance ſhall ariſe from another place, but ye, and your houſe ſhall periſh; I</hi> ſay, is not this <hi>word</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> beginning to be fulfilled upon <hi>you,</hi> who took not warning, when from the <hi>Lord God</hi> (as <hi>it</hi> was told <hi>you) it</hi> was <hi>a warning to you all;</hi> yea, that <hi>ye</hi> ſhould have <hi>blotted out the name of Amalek (i.e. the Principle that is againſt Liberty of Conſcience from under Heaven;</hi> yea, that <hi>ye ſhould not forget it;</hi> yea, that <hi>ye ſhould remember Amalck (i. e. the ſoul murthering, and Conſcience binding Clergy-man)</hi> and what <hi>he did unto you by the way, when ye were come out of Egypt; how he met you by the way, and ſmote the hindermoſt of you, even all the feeble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind you, when ye were faint and weary, and he feared not God, and that therefore ye ſhould blot out the name of Amalek from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Heaven.</hi> For at the moving of the Lord, that was wrote alſo; <hi>Amalek the firſt of the Nations,</hi> that <hi>warred againſt Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,</hi> when <hi>they</hi> were come out of <hi>Egypt, whoſe latter end ſhall be that he periſh for ever;</hi> as <hi>Balaam</hi> ſaid <hi>when his eyes were open, Cain Adams firſt born</hi> in the <hi>tranſgreſſion,</hi> who <hi>ſlew his Brother</hi> about <hi>Religion,</hi> becauſe his <hi>offering</hi> was <hi>accepted</hi> (and it was different) but <hi>Cains</hi> was not; <hi>Cain</hi> the <hi>fugitive,</hi> and <hi>vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bond,</hi> who <hi>is curſed from the Earth, which opened her mouth to receive his Brothers blood from his hand,</hi> the <hi>principle</hi> that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience, to be blotted out from under Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ye ſhall not forget it,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Lord</hi>) But <hi>ye</hi> have forgot <hi>it,</hi> and inſtead thereof endeavoured to record <hi>its</hi> name (which <hi>God will blot out, and remember what Amalek did, though ye have forgot it</hi>) when the <hi>Lord</hi> required the contrary, ſo <hi>ye</hi> have diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed the <hi>Commandement</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> therefore <hi>the Kingdome is rent from you, and is given to a neighbour of yours; that is
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119149:23"/> better than you;</hi> And have <hi>broken the Covenant of the wife of your youth, therefore will I Judge you, ſaith the Lord, as women that break wedlock, and ſhed blood, are judged, and I will give your blood in fury, and jealouſie, for a ſhort work is the Lord making in the Earth, yet a remnant of you ſhall return, even a remnant, unto the mighty God, and the Conſumption decreed, ſhall overflow with righteouſneſs;</hi> The <hi>day</hi> is at <hi>hand,</hi> the <hi>Lord hath ſpoken it.</hi> And though <hi>Agag</hi> the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Amalek,</hi> whom <hi>Saul</hi> and the <hi>People,</hi> (contrary to the commandment of the <hi>Lord)</hi> have <hi>ſpared alive,</hi> may <hi>come delicately to Samuel</hi> (the <hi>Prophet</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> who ſaid to <hi>Saul, thus ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that which Amalek did to Iſrael, how he laid wait for him in the way, when he came up from Egypt; now go, and ſmite Amalek, and utterly deſtroy all that they have, and ſpare them not, but ſlay both man and woman, infant and ſuckling, Oxe and Sheep, Camel and Aſs)</hi> and though <hi>Agag</hi> may ſay, <hi>ſurely the bitterneſs of Death is paſt,</hi> yet <hi>Samuel</hi> ſhall ſay, <hi>as thy ſword hath made wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Childleſs, ſo ſhall thy Mother be Childleſs among women.</hi> And <hi>Samuel ſhall hew Agag in peeces before the Lord,</hi> even in <hi>Gilgal; he that can receive it, let him receive it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Ah my <hi>Friends,</hi> wherewithal ſhall <hi>I</hi> bewail <hi>you?</hi> How ſhall <hi>I</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>you?</hi> How ſoon are <hi>ye</hi> revolted? How ſoon are <hi>ye</hi> backſlid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and ſtarted aſide? How ſoon hath <hi>darkneſs</hi> overſpread <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>night</hi> covered <hi>you?</hi> How ſoon are <hi>your feet</hi> ſtuck faſt <hi>again</hi> in the mire? The <hi>honeſty</hi> that ſtirred in <hi>you,</hi> how ſoon is i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> plunged <hi>again</hi> into the <hi>Pit?</hi> Cryed <hi>ye</hi> not lately to the <hi>Lord</hi> in the <hi>day of your Diſtreſs?</hi> Said <hi>ye</hi> not what <hi>ye</hi> would do, if <hi>he</hi> would <hi>once more deliver you?</hi> And hath <hi>he</hi> not been <hi>gratious to you, at the voyce of your cry? When he heard it,</hi> did <hi>he</hi> not <hi>deliver you?</hi> And when <hi>he</hi> had delivered <hi>you,</hi> did <hi>he</hi> not warn <hi>you,</hi> as aforeſaid (for <hi>I</hi> was moved of <hi>him,</hi> and from <hi>his</hi> mouth <hi>I</hi> ſpake, and a witneſs <hi>I</hi> am for <hi>him</hi> for ever; yea, that <hi>ye</hi> ſhould <hi>bring forth fruit meet for Repentance?</hi> Were <hi>ye</hi> not told, <hi>that this was your day, your day of Tryal from the Lord; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was trying ye, and proving you, to ſee whether there was an heart in you to do according to all that he had ſaid (even that ye would fear him, and keep all his Commandements alwayes, that it might be well with you, &amp; your children after you forever)</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:119149:23"/> And that <hi>for that cauſe he had once more overthrown your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and in the thing wherein they dealt proudly, had ſhewn himſelf above them; and put the power of theſe Nations, into your hands to try you, and prove you, and to ſee whether ye would do as ye ſpake;</hi> yea, <hi>that it was your Hour of Tryal, wherein the Lord was trying you, to ſee, whether, being delivered, and having power in your hands, ye would ſtand by, and ſecure the Cauſe and your ſelves.</hi> And are the <hi>dawnings</hi> of <hi>your day</hi> ſo ſoon cloſed into <hi>Night?</hi> Are <hi>ye</hi> ſo ſoon tryed and found too light? Are theſe <hi>your fruits meet for Repentance</hi> (which muſt be <hi>repeneed</hi> of, if ever <hi>it</hi> be well with <hi>you)</hi> Are <hi>ye roſe</hi> ſo <hi>early, and corrupted all your doings?</hi> Are <hi>ye delivered, to commit ſuch an abhomination as this? Ah fooliſh people and unwiſe! of the Rock that begat you, how ſoon are ye unmindful; And how have ye forgotten God that formed you? And lightly eſteemed the Rock of your Salvation (they ſang his praiſe, they ſoon forgat his works, they waited not on his Counſel, they forgat God their Saviour, which had done great things in Egypt, wondrous works in the Land of Ham, and terrible things by the Red Sea. Many times did he deliver them, but they provoked him, with their Counſel, and were brought low for their iniquity; never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs he regarded their affliction, when he heard their cry, and he remembred for them his Covenant, and repented according to the multitude of his mercies; He made them alſo to be pittyed of all thoſe that carryed them Captives, and had regard unto his name, that it might not be polluted among the Heathen:</hi> I ſay, Oh my <hi>Friends!</hi> How ſhall <hi>I</hi> lament <hi>you?</hi> Wherewithal ſhall <hi>I</hi> bewail you? Truly <hi>I</hi> bear a <hi>burthen</hi> of <hi>grief</hi> for <hi>you,</hi> and the <hi>weight</hi> thereof is <hi>heavy; Oh that my head were water, and mine eyes a Fountain of Tears, that I might weep day and night for you,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>day</hi> that <hi>I</hi> ſee <hi>is</hi> coming upon <hi>you, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ye Repent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My</hi> love was alwayes dear to <hi>you,</hi> with <hi>you I</hi> travailed (as a <hi>Fellow Member</hi> and otherwiſe) through the Difficulties <hi>ye</hi> met with from <hi>your</hi> firſt march to <hi>Windſor,</hi> to the <hi>late</hi> Interruption, wherein <hi>I</hi> bare not the leaſt part of the burthen, as there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong <hi>you</hi> can witneſs.</p>
               <p>In the <hi>late</hi> Interruption <hi>I</hi> was not, but was againſt <hi>it</hi> (for this
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119149:24"/> Reaſon (among others) becauſe <hi>I</hi> foreſaw (it being ſhewn me of the <hi>Lord)</hi> what hath ſince been attempted, and for that <hi>I</hi> alſo knew and obſerved the workings of <hi>him</hi> (and <hi>he</hi> knew it) that miſſ-led <hi>you,</hi> from <hi>Worceſter</hi> fight to <hi>that</hi> time; yea, <hi>I</hi> obſerved how that Principle entred and wrought, from the time of <hi>his</hi> (and many of your) falling under the <hi>King, by an Heart of unbelief,</hi> aſſoon as <hi>he</hi> and <hi>you</hi> were delivered) by the <hi>Spirit</hi> that roſe in the <hi>Souldiery,</hi> and the <hi>inferiour</hi> Officers at <hi>Triploe</hi> Heath, from the <hi>Major</hi> party in <hi>Parliament,</hi> which <hi>voted you Traytors</hi> unheard, for <hi>your</hi> Innocent Petition intended to be preſented them by <hi>your</hi> General, for things neceſſary to you as <hi>Souldiers,</hi> and ordered <hi>your</hi> disbanding as aforeſaid, <hi>which ſpirit</hi> (as <hi>I</hi> have ſaid) <hi>he</hi> (and many of you) falling under, (viz. upon <hi>diſtruſt,</hi> how, as the caſe ſtood then with <hi>you) ye</hi> ſhould be able to carry it againſt <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Presbyter</hi> in <hi>Parliament</hi> (who and <hi>their</hi> intereſt ye expected, would be united againſt <hi>you, he</hi> being, at that time in <hi>their</hi> cuſtody) upon that <hi>your</hi> new Engagement (not minding the <hi>Arm</hi> that had delivered <hi>you</hi> ſo oft, and but <hi>then</hi> had wrought <hi>your</hi> Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, to a <hi>Miracle,</hi> and ſo taking into <hi>your</hi> Cuſtody, out of the <hi>Parliaments,</hi> the <hi>King</hi> whom <hi>ye</hi> had oppoſed, the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>King,</hi> or of <hi>Abſoluteneſs, Monarchy</hi> or <hi>King-ſhip,</hi> againſt <hi>Civil Liberty</hi> (under which <hi>he,</hi> and many of <hi>you</hi> fell) then entred <hi>him</hi> (and many of <hi>you)</hi> as that of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> or the <hi>Spirit</hi> againſt <hi>Religious Liberty,</hi> or <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience (ye</hi> falling under it, <hi>by an heart of unbelief,</hi> aſſoon as <hi>ye</hi> were delivered, hath, <hi>now,</hi> into <hi>you,</hi> viz. upon <hi>diffidence,</hi> how (as was now <hi>your</hi> (caſe) <hi>ye</hi> ſhould buckle with the ſame generation engaged againſt <hi>ye</hi> in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>ye</hi> expected, would be much more now, upon that their <hi>Diſſolution</hi> (who ordered the <hi>Diſſolution</hi> of <hi>your</hi> Counſels, and <hi>ye</hi> know what that ſignified, even the <hi>Diſſolution</hi> of you) ſhould <hi>ye</hi> lay aſide their <hi>Coerſive</hi> Principle in <hi>matters</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> held forth in their intended Declaration for a Faſt, <hi>May</hi> 1659.</p>
               <p>And conſequently the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> upon that <hi>your new</hi> ſtate or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, (not conſidering <hi>your</hi> former, and but <hi>then aſtoniſhing</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance,) and ſo taking the <hi>Principle</hi> which <hi>ye</hi> had engaged againſt out of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> Declaration into your <hi>Addreſs, ye</hi> fell under <hi>it</hi> (as I have ſaid) and <hi>it</hi> entred into <hi>you</hi>) &amp; that <hi>Spirit</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:119149:24"/> of <hi>abſoluteneſs,</hi> being entred into <hi>him</hi> (who had ſo withſtood <hi>it,</hi> and cut <hi>it</hi> down) <hi>it</hi> never reſted till (as time &amp; opportunity would admit) <hi>it</hi> had wrought <hi>it</hi> ſelf into that <hi>Head-ſhip</hi> in <hi>him</hi> (thorough multitudes of <hi>diſguiſes</hi>) as <hi>it was</hi> at <hi>his</hi> Death, where <hi>It</hi> buried <hi>his</hi> Name and <hi>his</hi> Memory, and <hi>his</hi> valiant Acts, together with <hi>his</hi> Carcaſs, in the <hi>Pit</hi> of <hi>Infamy,</hi> and the <hi>Common-Wealth</hi>) which <hi>he</hi> trampled upon, and deſpiſed, and made ſo inexpreſſibly to ſuffer in order to this end, is roſe over <hi>him</hi> (as the <hi>ſame</hi> Spirit againſt <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> (Mark what <hi>I</hi> ſay, and <hi>remember for the time to come</hi>) will do by as many of <hi>you,</hi> as ſhall not <hi>ſpeedily repent</hi> (we will be to <hi>you,</hi> out of whom it is not <hi>purged till ye die</hi>) and <hi>Truth,</hi> the <hi>Dominion of God, in and over Conſcience, Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> (which that Spirit in this <hi>your</hi> Article hath trampled upon and deſpiſed, and <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Blood</hi> that hath been ſhed for <hi>it,</hi> and againſt which <hi>it</hi> purpoſely provided, as in <hi>that</hi> Article, and laid a foundation therein, to work <hi>it</hi> ſelf <hi>Lord over Conſcience,</hi> or <hi>Lord</hi> (as I may ſay) <hi>over the God of the ſpirits of all fleſh,</hi> who is <hi>Lord alone of Conſcience</hi> (as the <hi>other</hi> endeavoured over the <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> and will (through notable <hi>diſguiſes,</hi> yea more notable than have been yet) endeavour, and make to ſuffer, in order to this end, beyond what <hi>hath been,</hi> or <hi>will be after it; I</hi> ſay, <hi>Truth,</hi> the <hi>Dominion of God, in and over Conſcience, Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> ſhall (when <hi>it</hi> is as (yea more) unlikely, than was the <hi>late</hi> caſe of the <hi>Common-Wealth,</hi> yea (I may ſay) <hi>impoſſible</hi> as to men) <hi>riſe over your graves and carcaſſes, and Spirit, and Rule for ever. The Lord hath ſpoken</hi> it, and the <hi>things make haſt, bleſſed is he that endures to the end, the ſame ſhall be ſaved; ye</hi> may think <hi>theſe</hi> things <hi>ſtrange,</hi> but the <hi>time is at hand) I</hi> ſay, <hi>I</hi> was not for, but againſt the <hi>late</hi> Interruption, becauſe <hi>it</hi> was not only foreſhewn me by the <hi>Lord,</hi> even what hath ſince come to paſs, yea, that <hi>he</hi> would never return (as there are that can teſtifie, to whom <hi>I</hi> then told <hi>it</hi>) but <hi>I</hi> knew, and was within the <hi>Curtain</hi> of his <hi>Cable,</hi> or <hi>miſterious</hi> proceedings in order thereunto, and did often put <hi>checks</hi> to <hi>his</hi> carreir in <hi>that</hi> attempt (though <hi>ſingle</hi> and <hi>alone,</hi> for though <hi>I</hi> ſignified <hi>it</hi> to ſome <hi>Members</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> whom <hi>I</hi> could truſt, and propoſed a plain way for the prevention there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, yet <hi>they</hi> had <hi>no heart</hi> thereunto,) and at length, ſeeing how the <hi>deſign</hi> haſtened to an <hi>Iſſue,</hi> and that no <hi>Spirit</hi> appeared in them, whoſe <hi>proper</hi> work it was, to endeavour to cruſh <hi>it,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119149:25"/> no other way before <hi>me,</hi> in behalf of the Common-Wealth, (the <hi>Committee</hi> of the <hi>Coucil</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> for <hi>Examinations</hi> and <hi>Diſcoveries</hi> (of which <hi>I</hi> was <hi>Secretary</hi>) being <hi>unrevived,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a <hi>vote</hi> for that purpoſe, obtained of the <hi>New Counſel,</hi> November 1652. by <hi>him,</hi> for the ſecurity of <hi>his</hi> deſign) <hi>I</hi> cauſed <hi>it</hi> to be devulged, yea the <hi>very day,</hi> when <hi>it</hi> would be (and on which <hi>it</hi> was) <hi>done,</hi> if ſo be <hi>ſuch</hi> an <hi>Alarm</hi> might raiſe up a <hi>Spirit</hi> in the <hi>Parliament</hi> to prevent <hi>it,</hi> which <hi>it</hi> did not, nor could any thing hinder <hi>it, for the thing was of God,</hi> for the <hi>ſtayning of the pride and glory of Man,</hi> and the <hi>bringing about of his mighty works of wonder, for the glory of his Name, who alone will be known to be King, and to Rule in the Earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Since the <hi>Interruption,</hi> what <hi>I</hi> have <hi>done,</hi> and <hi>ſuffered, I</hi> ſpeak not, <hi>my life is given me for a prey</hi> (after all the <hi>Secret</hi> huntings after my <hi>blood) and my entegrity is with me,</hi> having a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> among <hi>men,</hi> as with the <hi>Lord,</hi> that <hi>as from the beginning I never betrayed, nor acted contrary to my Principle, nor was induced there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, upon any Temptation whatſoever, neither valuing my life, nor what I had, in relation to the Common-Wealth, ſo I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to this day, mourning</hi> with <hi>them</hi> that <hi>mourned,</hi> and <hi>weeping</hi> for them who <hi>wept</hi> for it.</p>
               <p>When the <hi>late</hi> hour was, <hi>I</hi> felt <hi>your</hi> burthen, and the <hi>weight</hi> of the <hi>powers</hi> of <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> which ſought to overwhelm, and obſtruct <hi>you,</hi> and the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>God wrought through me,</hi> which overcame <hi>your</hi> difficulties and overthrew <hi>your</hi> enemies, even at the <hi>very</hi> inſtant (as there be that can bear me witneſs, to whom I ſignified here what was doing, at the time of <hi>its</hi> Action) <hi>ye</hi> being deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>I</hi> waited, and with much <hi>gladneſs</hi> of <hi>heart,</hi> received whatſoever the <hi>Lord</hi> ſhewed <hi>me</hi> and required to write in order to <hi>your</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and ſent it to <hi>you,</hi> that <hi>ye</hi> might be preſerved, which <hi>was the earneſt deſire and breathing of my Soul, yea, that it might have been ſo, I could freely have been offered up in the will of the Lord,</hi> ſo <hi>dear</hi> were <hi>ye,</hi> to <hi>me;</hi> and leaſt <hi>ye</hi> ſhould <hi>back-ſlide,</hi> and <hi>fall under Temptation again,</hi> and that <hi>inrecoverably, I</hi> haſted that warning to <hi>you,</hi> as <hi>I</hi> was <hi>moved</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> unto which <hi>ye</hi> having not took heed, but being fallen, <hi>I</hi> am faithful in ſhewing <hi>you</hi> what <hi>ye</hi> have done, and what will <hi>aſſuredly</hi> befall <hi>you</hi> except <hi>ye</hi> repent, as I have received from the <hi>Lord;</hi> and ſo having <hi>born my Teſtimony,</hi> and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119149:25"/> 
                  <hi>fulfilled</hi> the <hi>will</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and <hi>ſuffered</hi> the <hi>ſore</hi> travail of <hi>this laſt hour</hi> that <hi>is</hi> to come, as <hi>I</hi> did of the <hi>former</hi> before <hi>it came,</hi> and <hi>wept over your graves, I</hi> reſt in <hi>peace,</hi> being aſſured, that <hi>as I have lived to ſee that day over, ſo I ſhall, to ſee this;</hi> and <hi>that the word which I have ſpoken in the name of the Lord, he will fulfill;</hi> and that <hi>he that hath betrayed you, into this, ſhall bear his burthen;</hi> and that <hi>judgment ſhall run down as waters,</hi> and <hi>righteouſneſs, as a Mighty ſtream in England.</hi> And <hi>that the end of the Lord in the Wars ſhall be accompliſhed, in their time and ſeaſon, but not in the way, or in the time, nor after the manner, that man expects it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not that <hi>we</hi> deſire, or need <hi>your</hi> Protection, do <hi>I</hi> thus write, nor that <hi>we</hi> are offended, in the leaſt, at this <hi>your</hi> proviſion, as to us; <hi>nay,</hi> be it known unto <hi>you,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Nations, <hi>our Truſt alone,</hi> is in the <hi>name</hi> of <hi>the Lord,</hi> who as <hi>he</hi> hath <hi>opened his peoples graves, and raiſed his ſeed out of it, in deſpight of all the powers of Darkneſs; and hath carried on his ſeed thus far, under the ſhelter of his wings, through multitudes of ſufferings; ſo he will not reſt till he hath ſet it over the heads of all its enemies.</hi> And <hi>verily this generation ſhall not paſs, till this be fulfilled.</hi> Yea, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do <hi>I</hi> expect (and ſo <hi>I</hi> did whileſt <hi>your</hi> late affairs ſeemed moſt promiſing to the contrary) the <hi>greateſt</hi> Tryals that <hi>have been yet,</hi> than a <hi>freedome</hi> from <hi>them.</hi> Becauſe, <hi>I</hi> know, that <hi>before the ſeed of God reign over all, it muſt be tryed to the uttermoſt, and the day haſtens, yea, the hour approacheth, wherein the ſon of man ſhall be betrayed into the hands of ſinners, who ſhall do unto the ſeed of God, whatſoever his hand, and his Counſel hath before determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be done; then ſhall God raiſe it over all, and crown it in his enemies ſight;</hi> therefore, <hi>Judas, what thou haſt to do, do quickly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe things <hi>I</hi> ſignifie, that when <hi>they</hi> come to paſs, <hi>ye</hi> may remember that <hi>ye</hi> were told of <hi>them</hi> before; <hi>I</hi> ſay, I write not <hi>this,</hi> for that <hi>we</hi> deſire or need <hi>your</hi> protection (though if <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity</hi> and <hi>faithfulneſs, activity,</hi> and <hi>diligence, fighting,</hi> and <hi>ſuffering,</hi> for the <hi>Nations Rights</hi> in <hi>General,</hi> do beſpeak <hi>our</hi> right to enjoy them in particular (as without controverſie it doth) <hi>we</hi> ought to have as much as <hi>any;</hi> yea, <hi>full freedome in ſoul and body is our due,</hi> and the <hi>due</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>theſe Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> But <hi>this I</hi> write in <hi>Bowels</hi> of <hi>love</hi> to <hi>you,</hi> that <hi>ye</hi> may <hi>ſee</hi> and be convinced of the evil of <hi>your</hi> doing, that ſo <hi>the fierce
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119149:26"/> wrath of the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which is ready, to break forth, and will light on the head of the wicked, may be turned away from you;</hi> For <hi>from the Lord of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> conſumption even deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined on the whole earth,</hi> and <hi>wee</hi> will be to <hi>them, by whom his ſeed is betrayed and ſuffers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo <hi>I</hi> am, and the <hi>Lord</hi> is, clear of <hi>your blood,</hi> and the <hi>word</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> which came to <hi>me,</hi> at <hi>Briſtol,</hi> the 23. day of the third moneth, called <hi>May,</hi> 1659, upon reading <hi>this</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of <hi>your</hi> Addreſs, word for word, in the <hi>News Books,</hi> as voted by the <hi>Parliament;</hi> viz. <hi>Son of man, wilt thou not judge them? wilt thou not judge them?</hi> yea, <hi>declare to them their abhomination, I</hi> have <hi>fulfilled.</hi> It concerns <hi>you</hi> to mind what <hi>I</hi> have ſaid, and <hi>me</hi> to wait, till the <hi>appointed end.</hi> And ſo <hi>I</hi> have <hi>finiſhed</hi> this <hi>my.</hi> Teſtimony.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>GEORGE BISHOP.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:119149:26"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
